Log on, gem!
ログインしてください、宝石さん！
Let me present to you...
あなたにプレゼントしましょう...
the famous RPC Sóng M alguien
有名なRPCソン・マルギエン
from Hanyang in Pohbank
漢陽発ポーバンク
Episode 14
第14話
Please welcome Mr.P Hong Xœ bother ASL
P Hon Xœ さん、ASL をよろしくお願いします
Teacher, Academician Wang and all the guests
王先生、アカデミー会員、そしてゲストの皆様
Colleagues in the hospital, good night everyone
入院中の同僚、皆さんおやすみ
It is a great pleasure to invite Professor Chen Zhuting today
本日は陳珠庭教授をお招きできることを大変うれしく思います
Come give knowledge Try this speech
知識を与えに来てください このスピーチを試してください
Professor Chen's Basic Experience
チェン教授の基礎経験
in the speech
スピーチの中で
But I can reveal a lot.
しかし、多くのことを明らかにすることができます。
Because he and I are colleagues at National Taiwan University
なぜなら彼と私は国立台湾大学の同僚だからです
20 years
20年
his office is next door to mine
彼のオフィスは私の隣にあります
So I have worked with you for many years
それで私はあなたと何年も一緒に仕事をしてきました
he is very easy to recognize
彼はとても分かりやすいです
when you speak
あなたが話すとき
it's his hair
それは彼の髪です
then very elegant
それからとてもエレガントです
Then
それから
We are the Beethoven of chemistry
私たちは化学のベートーベンです
You can see her image is very similar to that photo of Beethoven
彼女のイメージがベートーベンの写真に非常に似ていることがわかります。
so you'll remember
だからあなたは覚えているでしょう
That Mr. Chen
あのチェンさん
National Taiwan University is mine
国立台湾大学は私のものです
He is my student in the chemistry department
彼は化学科の私の生徒です
Then after going abroad
それから海外に行ってからは
Go to Emerging Natti University
新興のナッティ大学へ行く
And Ai Hehua
そして愛和華
Ph.D. from State University
州立大学博士号取得
Then did a postdoc at Penn State
その後ペンシルベニア州立大学でポスドクを務めた
Returned to National Taiwan University to teach in about 1985
1985年頃に国立台湾大学に戻り教鞭をとる
in teaching
教える上で
very popular with students
学生にとても人気があります
Research is also well done
研究も充実している
Received the Outstanding Research Award from the National Science Council
米国学術会議より優秀研究賞を受賞
In recent years very
近年ではとても
This cares about the general education of the university
これは大学の一般教育を重視します
science education
科学教育
so this
したがって、この
also did this
これもやった
The director of the chemistry center of the entire Taiwan chemical community
台湾化学コミュニティ全体の化学センター所長
And now this is National Taiwan University
そしてここが国立台湾大学です
Science Education Development Center
科学教育開発センター
He put a small one outside
彼は小さなものを外に置いた
Panford
パンフォード
that
それか
Science Education Development Center
科学教育開発センター
he puts a lot of effort
彼はとても努力します
that is now
それは今です
Uh, for example, his Discovery series
たとえば、彼のディスカバリー シリーズ
Already the seventh installment of the Discovery series
すでにディスカバリーシリーズの7作目
This exploration series is very fun
この探索シリーズはとても楽しいです
Uh, there are about six long and eight long in one semester.
えー、一学期に長めが6つ、長めが8つくらいあります。
weekend speech
週末のスピーチ
Music Institute at National Taiwan University
国立台湾大学音楽研究所
This weekend from two to four
今週末の2時から4時まで
something like this
このようなもの
then no credit
それならクレジットはありません
I don't care about the guests
ゲストのことなんて気にしてないよ
But the students participated enthusiastically
しかし生徒たちは熱心に参加してくれました
It's like there were 400 people last time
前回は400人くらいだったような
When the classroom is full, the outside is also full
教室がいっぱいになると外もいっぱいになる
This is what he promotes. This year is the seventh issue of the exploration series.
探検シリーズは今年で7号目となる。
So you know he puts a lot of effort into
彼が多大な努力を払っていることはご存知でしょう
On the development of science education
科学教育の発展について
I think he will have his own characteristics when he comes on stage
ステージに立つと彼自身の特徴が出てくると思います
easily you will remember him later
後で簡単に彼のことを思い出すでしょう
All Taiwanese high school teachers
台湾の高校教師の皆さん
Everyone in Taiwan remembers him as a very special
台湾の誰もが彼を特別な人として覚えています
unique style
ユニークな格好
This year he will also talk about a very unique topic
今年も非常にユニークなテーマについて話します
Energy and Sustainable Civilization
エネルギーと持続可能な文明
We clap hands to welcome Professor Chen
手をたたいてチェン教授を歓迎します
Thanks
ありがとう
Thank you Vice President Peng
彭副社長に感謝します
This is really unreasonable
これは本当に無理がある
He does have an office next door to mine
彼は私の隣にオフィスを持っています
So I have been the care of Vice President Peng for so many years
私は長年にわたり彭副総統の世話をしてきました。
I'm going to this precious place today
今日はこの大切な場所へ行きます
I really feel a little bit like selling articles in front of Confucius
孔子の前で品物を売るような気分になる
Especially vice president Peng will fly to Europe tonight
特に彭副主席は今夜ヨーロッパに飛びます
I really feel a little unworthy
本当に少し不甲斐ない気がする
Then he specially invited Academician Wang Yi over to say
それから彼は特別に学者の王毅を招待してこう言いました。
The following Q&A and the ending part should be annoyed to Academician Wang Yi
以下のQ&Aと最後の部分は、王毅学者を怒らせるはずです。
So two good colleagues and good friends can come here today
今日は二人の良き同僚と良き友人がここに来られます
let myself be a little pampered
少しだけ自分を甘やかしてあげましょう
Of course, I rarely feel nervous when I give a speech.
もちろん、スピーチをするときに緊張することはほとんどありません。
I just mentioned it to Professor Tang Pingzhe
先ほど唐平哲教授に話しました。
So here's a lot of familiar faces I've seen
ここに私が見たたくさんのおなじみの顔があります
Colleagues, good friends of Zhongyuan Institute
中原学院の同僚、良き友人たち
Hello everyone
こんにちは、みんな
And good night, viewers
そしておやすみ、視聴者の皆さん
Thanks
ありがとう
I actually struggled for a long time
実は長い間苦労しました
I have been thinking about what kind of topic to use for this speech
このスピーチにどんなテーマを使おうかずっと考えています
It's a feast of knowledge, I know we should talk about something more popular
これは知識の饗宴だ、もっと人気のあるものについて話すべきだとわかっている
But if you want to enter Academia Sinica
しかし、中央研究院に入学したい場合は、
I always feel that it is better to have a little professionalism behind
私はいつも、少しプロ意識を持ったほうがいいと思っています。
But I still chose this topic
それでも私はこのテーマを選びました
Express my recent concerns
最近の懸念を表明する
Some have gone beyond chemistry
化学を超えたものもある
Although Ren Yuan still has a very close relationship with chemistry
レン・ユアンは今でも化学と非常に密接な関係にありますが、
But in what I'm going to report today
しかし、今日私が報告する内容では、
You can see that many but not all of the questions I asked were
私が尋ねた質問のすべてではありませんが、多くの質問が次のとおりであることがわかります。
Especially most likely not chemistry problems
特に化学の問題ではない可能性が高い
If I continue, I will give lectures related to chemistry
このまま続けたら化学関連の講義をします
maybe please include
たぶん含めてください
The other is that sustainable civilization is actually a question that is often raised by people nowadays.
もう一つは、持続可能な文明というのは、実は現代の人々からよく提起される問題だということです。
Then I want to emphasize a little bit to everyone.
それから皆さんに少し強調したいことがあります。
After all, when a scientist looks at something like this
結局のところ、科学者がこのようなものを見ると、
Do you have any unique perspectives?
何かユニークな視点はありますか？
The crisis for everyone is now whether domestic or foreign
国内でも海外でも、今はすべての人にとっての危機です
A question that everyone pays close attention to
誰もが注目する質問
but there is a problem in taiwan
しかし台湾にも問題がある
As long as it is a very hot topic or problem
それが非常にホットなトピックや問題である限り、
Then everyone will find a self-shooting answer to it.
そうすれば誰もがそれに対する自撮りの答えを見つけるでしょう。
Then everyone is very familiar with this thing, we have all heard of it
それでは、誰もがこのことについてよく知っており、誰もがそれについて聞いたことがあるでしょう
In fact, is everyone’s crisis really serious in Taiwan?
実際のところ、台湾の皆さんの危機は本当に深刻なのでしょうか？
I believe this question is not so easy to answer
この質問に答えるのはそれほど簡単ではないと思います
But let's see if you go to Crisis Encyclopedia to find the definition
しかし、その定義を見つけるために危機百科事典に行ってみてみましょう。
Everyone's crisis actually refers to when your personnel, especially in terms of economics, he emphasized
全員の危機とは、実際には、特に経済的な観点から、従業員の危機を指します。
When you have difficulties in working needs
仕事上のニーズに困ったとき
He has bottleneck congestion
彼にはボトルネックの輻輳がある
We already said he can use crisis
彼は危機を利用できるとすでに言いました
I remember myself paying more attention to this noun
私自身、この名詞にもっと注目していたのを覚えています
It happened to be when I first came to America
初めてアメリカに来たときのことだった
At that time, cars were also expensive, and gasoline was also expensive.
当時は車も高価でしたし、ガソリンも高価でした。
Then all the graduate students suddenly couldn't find a job
すると大学院生全員が突然就職できなくなった
So it's obviously not just this that Yong shot
つまり、ヨンが撃ったのは明らかにこれだけではありません
ordinary economic problems
通常の経済問題
But what everyone feels more easily recently should be
でも、最近みんなが感じやすくなっているのは、
In terms of interesting electricity prices, oil prices,
興味深い電気料金や石油価格に関しては、
Immediately it has been reflected that it will rise
すぐに上がると反映されました
For Taiwan, everyone has been arguing a lot lately
台湾については、最近みんなよく議論しています
If you look at this table
この表を見ると
Is an Exon XN in the US their oil company
米国の石油会社 Exon XN です
A report given in 2004
2004年に発表された報告書
This is the 2004 report
これは 2004 年のレポートです
It is above the work area, the green area
作業エリア・緑地の上にあります
Already seen in 2004
2004年にはすでに見られていた
that is to say they are
つまり彼らはそうです
In terms of the output that can be provided
提供できるアウトプットに関しては
Already in a downward trend
すでに下落傾向にある
But
しかし
The world's demand is going up in reverse
世界の需要は逆に高まっている
This is 2004
これは 2004 年のことです
you can tell
教えてもいいよ
They think the difference between supply and demand
彼らは需要と供給の違いを考えている
Already at least 4% to 6%
すでに少なくとも 4% ～ 6%
The gap above this
この上の隙間
So far, 2012 is obviously in
今では明らかに2012年に入っています
Here you can see the gap increase
ここでギャップが拡大しているのがわかります
is multiplied several times
数倍になる
Indicates the current situation of personnel crisis
人材危機の現状を示す
Compare
比較
In the past few years, the difference is much more
ここ数年でその差はさらに大きくなった
So we use another table to look at the oil price and see that the oil price is actually what he just uploaded
そこで、別のテーブルを使用して原油価格を調べ、その原油価格が実際に彼がアップロードしたものであることを確認します。
oil price
原油価格
This is a more professional way of saying we don't care about him
これは、私たちは彼のことを気にしていないと言う、より専門的な方法です
You can see it in this trend
この傾向を見ればわかります
This one is the most obvious and it was two years ago
これが最も明白で、2年前のものです
economic tsunami
経済津波
caused by
所造成的
Oil prices per barrel break through
バレルあたりの原油価格が突破
$140
140美元
That
それか
Actually it's probably closer to 150
実際は150近くあるかもしれない
So this signal is very obvious
したがって、この信号は非常に明白です
But what I am asking everyone to pay attention to now is not just this signal.
しかし、私が今皆さんに注意してほしいのは、この信号だけではありません。
but from 2003
しかし2003年から
Until now about 2012
2012年くらいまでは
Its overall trend is to run upwards
全体的な傾向は上昇傾向にあります
And looking back
そして振り返ってみると
it doesn't need another pick
別の選択は必要ありません
it directly this number
それは直接この番号です
might break through
突破するかもしれない
More than 140 or even 150 U.S. barrels
140、さらには 150 米国バレル以上
so in a short time
だから短時間で
such a rise
このような上昇
This is why our
だからこそ私たちの
My senior, Vice President Peng's junior
私の先輩、彭副総統の後輩です。
Minister of Xie Enxiang Yuan
謝恩祥院的部長
It was the first class in Takao's class in the Department of Chemical Medicine
化学医科大学の高尾先生の授業の最初の授業でした
you see obviously he has a headache
明らかに彼は頭痛を​​抱えていることがわかります
In fact, it should be our headache.
実際、それは私たちの頭の痛い問題であるはずです。
Because this is at least a 10% increase
これは少なくとも 10% の増加であるため、
is about to see
見ようとしています
So these two slides show
この 2 つのスライドは、
Equal to the crisis is a problem all over the world
危機は世界中で問題になっている
But I think there is one more important thing
でも、もう一つ重要なことがあると思う
In fact, it is for Taiwan
実は台湾にとっては
Might be a big problem too
それも大きな問題かもしれない
There is an important reason is
重要な理由があります
Taiwan actually has almost no natural energy
実は台湾には自然エネルギーがほとんどない
That looks tricky
それは難しいようです
If we all rely on the outside
もし私たち全員が外側に頼ったら
what to do next
次はどうする
Of course, from the perspective of economic development
もちろん経済発展の観点からも
this is a problem
これは問題だ
this is my first question
これが私の最初の質問です
I may ask a lot of questions today
今日はたくさん質問するかもしれません
In fact, I will not provide an answer
実際には答えは出しません
I'm thinking
考えています
All our people and experts in Taiwan
台湾のすべての従業員と専門家
should all come face to face with us
みんなで私たちと向き合ってみるべきだ
things to face
直面するもの
I have a lot of stories to tell today
今日は話したいことがたくさんあります
The first one I talked about is Easter Island in the Pacific
最初に話したのは太平洋のイースター島です
This is Glass Muscia
こちらはグラスムシアです
in the Pacific Ocean
太平洋で
the easternmost island
最東端の島
In such a big cloud head
こんなに大きな雲の頭の中で
it's actually invisible
それは実際には目に見えない
Taiwan can be found in this place at least on the map
台湾は少なくとも地図上ではこの場所にあります
Actually Easter Island is closer
実はイースター島の方が近いんです
South America so actually belongs to Chile
南アメリカは実際にはチリに属します
such a small island
こんなに小さな島
its most special thing
その最も特別なこと
is it along all the coastlines
すべての海岸線沿いにありますか
There are many people's head portraits standing
たくさんの人の顔写真が立っています
Some are standing to watch the sunrise
日の出を見るために立っている人もいます
Some are standing to watch the sunset
夕日を眺めるために立っている人もいます
So often a whole row by the sea
海沿いに一列になることもよくある
You can see this giant stone statue
この巨大な石像が見えます
been full for a while
しばらく満席だった
more than a hundred years
百年以上
It's because everyone doesn't know why it looks like this
なんでこんな風になっているのかみんな分からないから
will be there
そこにいるでしょう
Of course this gives us Taiwan
もちろんこれで台湾が得られます
Especially the key report of Taiwan
特に台湾に関する重要なレポート
such programs
そのようなプログラム
one of my life's big wishes
私の人生の大きな願いの一つ
just hold a new event
新しいイベントを開催するだけ
The new program called Non-Critical Reports
非クリティカルレポートと呼ばれる新しいプログラムと呼ばれる
They said this thing was visited by aliens
彼らはこれを宇宙人が訪れたと言った
What has been what a ladder
はしごは何だったのか
What did the visit say a lot
訪問中はどんな話をしましたか？
This island is actually quite special.
実はこの島はかなり特殊なのです。
Because when the Europeans went to the island
なぜなら、ヨーロッパ人がこの島に行ったとき、
They're actually a lost island
実は彼らは失われた島なのです
But a few hundred years ago
しかし数百年前
he used to have a coconut tree for the restaurant
彼はレストランにココナッツの木を植えていた
It is better than the one from National Taiwan University
国立台湾大学のものよりも優れています
And there is this so-called great prince in the Central Plains Court
そして、このいわゆる偉大な王子が中原法廷にいます
taller coconut tree
背の高いヤシの木
the whole island is coconut grove
島全体がコ​​コナッツ畑です
It's really a forest of coconut trees
まさにヤシの森です
you can see the back of this
これの裏側が見えます
almost photogenic
ほぼフォトジェニック
So its decline and the change of resources on it
その衰退とそれに伴う資源の変化
In fact, it has a lot to do with
実はそれと大きく関係があるのです
Another thing is that the Maya of America
もう一つは、アメリカのマヤ族です。
This is another place where aliens have been
ここもおそらく宇宙人が訪れたことのある場所です
OK
OK
We still have a few places that we can look at one by one
まだ一つ一つ見ていきたいところがいくつかあります
words of aztec civilization
アステカ文明の言葉
from the thirteenth century to the seventeenth century
およそ13世紀から17世紀にかけて
you can see their temple of the sun
彼らの太陽の神殿が見えます
In fact, there are many pyramids in Egypt.
実際、エジプトにはピラミッドがたくさんあります。
There is a little specific flavor
少し独特の風味があります
In fact, there are movies that have already been filmed
実はすでに撮影済みの映画もあるんです
In fact, they often do restricted activities when they go up.
実際、彼らは上昇時に制限された活動を行うことがよくあります。
But the whole building feels very modern
でも建物全体はとてもモダンな感じです
That is to say they are very primitive looking although limited in activity
つまり、活動は限られているものの、外見は非常に原始的であるということです。
Many places in their buildings actually seem to be related to mathematics
彼らの建物の多くの場所は実際に数学に関連しているようです
In fact, there is also an astronomical relationship.
実は天文学的な関係もあります。
Composite is pretty good
コンポジットはかなり良い
This is actually not very strange
これは実際にはそれほど奇妙ではありません
Because a building like this is actually a human tool
こういう建物って実は人間の道具だから
Human tools without support from mathematics and physics
数学や物理学のサポートを必要としない人間のツール
By experience, people have had a long time
経験上、人々は長い間
Can show very brilliant achievements in architecture
建築分野で非常に輝かしい成果を示すことができる
Of course, in addition to that, they are full of special
もちろんそれ以外にもスペシャルな内容が満載です
They have some special astrological characters
彼らはいくつかの特別な占星術的特徴を持っています
These astrological characters are comparisons
これらの占星術の文字は比較です
early travel
早めの旅行
Comparing text that is not a monogram
モノグラムではないテキストの比較
Now many of them have been revealed
今ではその多くが明らかになりました
It can be seen that this civilization
この文明が
In fact, it has its degree of brilliance
実際、輝きには程度があります
Of course, including some of their statues
もちろん、彼らの彫像の一部も含めて
These statues are even more
これらの彫像はさらに素晴らしいです
There are many key reports that are full of words.
言葉が詰まった重要なレポートがたくさんあります。
The other one in Blue America is the Inca civilization
ブルーアメリカのもう一つはインカ文明です
exactly in central america and blue america
まさに中央アメリカとブルーアメリカ
The timing of the two shaking echoes is not very consistent
2 つの揺れるエコーのタイミングはあまり一致していません
this is a little later
これは少し後です
Around the 15th, 40th and 16th centuries
15世紀、40世紀、16世紀頃
It was later wiped out by the Europeans
その後ヨーロッパ人によって滅ぼされました
Inca kingdom it's actually a very special one
インカ王国は実際には非常に特別な王国です
It's on the hills of Kalamahah
カラマハの丘の上です
There are very high mountains with very delicate buildings
非常に高い山があり、非常に繊細な建物があります
Inside this exquisite building
この立派な建物の中に
Including very complex irrigation facilities and
非常に複雑な灌漑施設や
The constructed system
構築されたシステム
These systems are very
これらのシステムは非常に
researched a lot
たくさん調べた
In about National Geographic
ナショナル ジオグラフィックについて
is the country's first magazine
この国初の雑誌です
it already has a lot of videos
すでにたくさんのビデオがあります
can introduce
紹介できる
How are these buildings made?
これらの建物はどのように作られるのでしょうか？
is a very detailed building
非常に精緻な建物です
talking about this
これについて話す
This is one of the reasons why I am interested
これが私が興味を持っている理由の一つです
I probably will today
たぶん今日はそうするだろう
not the first time
初めてではない
I will mention it a few times later
後で何回か言及します
the representatives such a person
代表はこんな人
because the man he wrote the basic book
なぜなら彼は基本的な本を書いた人だからです
in my recent years
ここ数年で
When the general education courses offered by Taiwan University at the beginning of the year
台湾大学が開講する一般教養科目が年度初めに始まると、
have used his book
彼の本を使いました
as a textbook
教科書として
because answered me some
いくつか答えてくれたので
very important question
非常に重要な質問
This is a thicker book
これは分厚い本です
called Clares
クレアと呼ばれる
Chinese translation into big collapse
大崩壊の中国語訳
Should be China Times
チャイナタイムズであるべきだ
The times see what they say
時代は彼らの言うことを見ます
Times Publishing is their book
タイムズ・パブリッシングは彼らの本です
This one should have won a Pulis Award
これはピューリス賞を受賞すべきだった
His book is called Da Bang Huai
彼の本は「Da Bang Huai」です。
Another word to repeat
もう一度繰り返す言葉
in a society
社会の中で
how to choose
選び方
whether they succeed or fail
彼らが成功するか失敗するか
I believe no society
私はどんな社会も信じない
Will hope to choose to go down the road of failure
失敗の道を進むことを選択することを望むだろう
But at the end
しかし最後には
Why are they such a brilliant civilization
なぜ彼らはこれほど輝かしい文明を持っているのでしょうか
unsustainable
持続不可能な
can't continue
続けられない
these splendid civilizations
これらの素晴らしい文明
What kind of mistake did you make?
どのような間違いを犯しましたか?
Or encountered some kind of scourge
あるいは何らかの災難に遭遇した
make them suffer
彼らを苦しませる
sorry
ごめん
another question i want to ask
もう一つ聞きたい質問があります
that is
あれは
in every society
あらゆる社会で
We know that in modern terms
現代の言葉で言えば、私たちはそれを知っています
The average IQ is about the same
平均IQはほぼ同じ
But why some civilizations
しかし、なぜ一部の文明は
in a world
世界で
role played today
今日果たした役割
There are particularly prominent places
特に目立つ場所があります
Is it true that in some societies
一部の社会では本当ですか？
Its collective intelligence is higher
その集合知はより高い
collective intelligence
集合知
there is a higher place
もっと高い場所がある
Is the difference in height a personal material inside?
身長差は個人的な内面の材料なのでしょうか？
There is a difference between the average and the high and low
平均と最高と最低には差がある
What kind of society is it that reaches some consensus
何らかの合意が得られる社会とはどのような社会なのか
make them make decisions that lead to death
死につながる決断をさせる
Some are destined for greater glory
より大きな栄光を運命づけられている人もいる
So if you see our Taiwan Legislative Yuan
ですから、私たちの台湾立法院を見たら、
You will wonder why a group of
なぜグループなのか不思議に思うでしょう。
It stands to reason that smart people will work together to make some
賢い人々が協力して何かを生み出すのは当然のことです
stupid thing
愚かなこと
For many years their names were worn on their vests
長年にわたり、彼らの名前はベストに着られていました
So we don't have to figure out who it is.
したがって、それが誰であるかを理解する必要はありません。
Fortunately, this is in the Legislative Yuan
幸いなことに、これは立法院にあります
If this kind of thing happened in college
大学でこんな事があったら
This problem becomes serious
この問題は深刻になります
So in my speech today
それで、今日の私のスピーチでは
Its outline will probably be discussed from several different projects
その概要はおそらくいくつかの異なるプロジェクトから議論されるでしょう
Maybe it's because I'm a scientist personally
おそらくそれは私が個人的に科学者だからかもしれません
I will definitely learn from the energy in the universe and nature
宇宙や自然のエネルギーから必ず学びます
talk about these things
これらのことについて話す
Yes and then of course it will soon cut to life and human
はい、そしてもちろん、それはすぐに生命と人間に切り込まれます
go inside the circle
輪の中に入る
love with people
人々との愛
In fact, it is closely related
実は密接に関係しているのです
And the development of every civilization
そしてあらゆる文明の発展
It's all about popularity
すべては人気の問題だ
I'm not actually very detailed
実はあまり詳しくないんですが
Let's talk about the details
詳細について話しましょう
because of our problem
私たちの問題のせいで
will focus on popularity and sustainable civilization
人気と持続可能な文明に焦点を当てる
this photo is very famous
この写真はとても有名です
It's Apollo 17
アポロ17号です
in may be
かもしれない
late 60's
60年代的末期
Photos taken when I went to space
宇宙に行ったときに撮った写真
This one may be so far
これはもう遠いかも知れません
Photos of Earth are referenced
地球の写真が参照されています
one of the most pictures
最も多くの写真の 1 つ
you can see the arabian peninsula very clearly
アラビア半島がよく見えます
and the region from Africa all the way to Antarctica
そしてアフリカから南極までの地域
is very clear
とても明確です
in history
歴史の中で
not too many people have a chance
チャンスがある人はあまり多くない
able to see the landscape like this
こんな景色も見れます
see our hometown
私たちの故郷を見てください
The entire spherical shape can be seen very clearly
球全体の形状がくっきりと見えます
But if we look at it historically
しかし歴史的に見てみると
this Heraclitus
このヘラクレイトス
In fact strictly speaking
実は厳密に言えば
These are more philosophers
彼らはもっと哲学者です
i don't think we will
そうは思わない
treat them as scientists
彼らを科学者として扱う
when he was in greek times
彼がギリシャ時代にいたとき
sorry over here
ごめんなさい、こちら
not very clear
あまり明確ではない
Should be BC
BCのはず
Around the fifth or sixth century
5世紀か6世紀頃
He already mentioned one thing
彼はすでに一つのことについて言及しました
The world is actually a combination of many states
世界は実際には多くの国家の組み合わせです
And between these states and states
そしてこれらの州と州の間では
In fact, it has a rheological change
実際には、レオロジー変化が起こります
his famous saying
彼の有名な言葉
He said every morning a new sun rises
彼は毎朝新しい太陽が昇ると言いました
So he said fire is the source of all matter
それで彼は火がすべての物質の源だと言いました
That is, in Greece from about the third century to the fifth century
つまり、ギリシャでは3世紀から5世紀頃にかけて
people kept coming out and saying
人々は出てきて言い続けた
this world
この世界
The very rich and diverse landscapes we see
私たちが目にするとても豊かで多様な風景
In fact, there are very simple elements
実はとてもシンプルな要素があります
Telus was first proposed
Telus が最初に提案された
he said it was water
彼はそれは水だと言いました
But the green map master Herac said
しかし、緑の地図の達人ヘラックは言いました。
He said it should be fire
彼は火事になるはずだと言いました
when going from his point of view
彼の視点から見ると
lead to later clark
後のクラークにつながる
sorry it should be
ごめんなさい、そうあるべきです
I forgot the name
名前を忘れてしまいました
And then there's Aristotle, he's talking about the four elements
そしてアリストテレスが4つの要素について話しています
Your boss said he included fire as a key element.
あなたの上司は、重要な要素として火が含まれていると言いました。
But if it is in our modern times
でもそれが現代だったら
You saw a very important telescope in the 90s
90年代に非常に重要な望遠鏡を見ましたね
NASA put it in the sky
NASAが空に打ち上げた
We call it the Hubble Telescope because it's a memorial
記念碑なのでハッブル望遠鏡と呼んでいます
The one who said the universe is expanding
宇宙は膨張していると言ったのは
haber mentioned his name
ハーバーは自分の名前を挙げた
as the name of the telescope
望遠鏡の名前として
When it was put up, there were several kinds of lenses on it.
出品時は数種類のレンズが載っていました。
X-ray lens included Infrared lens included Ultraviolet lens included
X線レンズ付属 赤外線レンズ付属 紫外線レンズ付属
There are a lot of telescopic lenses on it
望遠レンズがたくさん付いています
In fact, when I first put it on, it seemed that one of the lenses was broken.
実際、初めて装着したとき、片方のレンズが割れてしまったように見えました。
So the space shuttle was sent up to recalibrate it.
そこで、スペースシャトルを再調整するために打ち上げられたのです。
replaced with a new one
新しいものと交換されました
This is a very important tool
これはとても重要なツールです
Since the family is slightly used in
家族も少し慣れてきたので、
After seeing the moons next to Jupiter with a telescope four hundred years ago
400年前に望遠鏡で木星の隣の衛星を見た後
After putting this on
これを履いた後は
What he saw turned out to be a very different landscape
彼が見たものはまったく異なる風景だった
Because of its Scope
範囲が広いため
We emphasize that this Scope is a field of vision
このスコープが視野であることを強調します。
It actually works on a telescope
実際に望遠鏡で動作します
Telescope is the field of view circled
望遠鏡は丸で囲んだ視野です
is right in the distance
すぐ近くにあります
This is exactly the same as Microscope, which is a microscope.
これは顕微鏡であるMicroscopeと全く同じです。
The field of view it circles is placed in a very close distance.
それに囲まれた視野は非常に近い距離に配置されます。
is a very different thing
それは全く違うものです
Scientists choose Scope
科学者はスコープを選択します
That is, our eyes are chosen
つまり私たちの目は選ばれているのです
see what the target above
上のターゲットが何であるかを見てください
makes us use the special method
特別な方法を使用させます
special tools see special things
特別な道具は特別なものを見る
This is a very important thing in the development of science
これは科学の発展において非常に重要なことです
The results provided
提供された結果
In fact, the one that proves that the universe is expanding is called
実際、宇宙が膨張していることを証明したものは、
The so-called Big Bang theory of the explosion
いわゆる爆発のビッグバン理論
you can tell
教えてもいいよ
We actually see pictures made of galaxies and clouds
私たちは実際に銀河や雲でできた写真を見ています
like fragments after an explosion
爆発後の破片のように
fly away form
飛び去る形
Such proof is actually not enough
そのような証拠は実際には十分ではありません
Another fact seen
もう一つ見えてきた事実
is the whole universe
宇宙全体です
it's actually in the process of exploding
それは実際に爆発しつつある
it's been a very long time
とても長い時間が経ちました
That is, the farthest light
つまり、一番遠い光
After collecting
回収後
We found that in fact the explosion time of the entire universe
実際、宇宙全体の爆発時間は
has been carried over to a very precise number
非常に正確な数値に引き継がれています
Relatively speaking, 13.7 billion years
相対的に言えば、137億年
i remember when i was studying
勉強していた時のことを思い出します
When studying in middle school and university
中学や大学で学ぶとき
The figure given at that time was about 10 billion to 15 billion
当時の数字は100億～150億程度
We already feel that it is not easy
私たちはそれが簡単ではないことをすでに感じています
very precise number
非常に正確な数字
Now what Haberwang has told us is that
さて、ハバワング氏が私たちに語った事は、
13.7 billion years
137億年的時間
during this time
この間
In fact, there is a point of time
実はタイミングというものがあって、
Where is this plot in the space
このプロットは空間内のどこにありますか
not sure
不太清楚
But after a big bang
しかしビッグバンの後
it keeps expanding
それは拡大し続けます
Inflation is actually spread out over an almost flat universe
インフレは実際にはほぼ平らな宇宙に広がっています
The expansion process of the explosion is not linear yet.
爆発の拡大プロセスはまだ直線的ではありません。
That is to say, it even has cases of accelerated expansion.
つまり、拡大が加速するケースさえある。
That is, if you look at it from the present point of view
つまり、今の視点から見ると、
The universe is actually still expanding
実は宇宙は今も膨張し続けている
But one important thing is
しかし、一つ重要なことは、
if you push it back
押し戻せば
Its basis is in fact
その根拠は実は
because it was a big bang
ビッグバンだったから
so it's a big energy
それは大きなエネルギーです
Transformation created matter after it exploded
爆発後に物質が変化して生成された
There is an interchanging state between man and matter
人間と物質の間には交流状態がある
for us now
今の私たちにとって
Today's science we have been able to describe
私たちが説明できるようになった今日の科学
Our universe has many examples that make up it
私たちの宇宙には、それを構成する多くの例があります
There are many examples of pillows especially on the earth
特に地球上には枕の例がたくさんあります
that is atoms
それは原子です
But if we look carefully
しかし、よく見てみると
The universe is not what we imagined
宇宙は私たちが想像していたものではありません
It's really the same as our earth
それは本当に私たちの地球と同じです
There are many principles
たくさんの原則があります
Main ingredient with wrinkle head
リンクルヘッドの主成分
Atomic substances are mainly pure and harmful elements
原子物質は主に純粋な元素と有害な元素です
If you have a little background in chemistry
化学の知識が少しある場合
At least clear is one of the simplest elements
少なくとも明確は最も単純な要素の 1 つです
Hazard is an element slightly heavier than it
ハザードはそれよりもわずかに重い要素です
But the combined weight of these two
しかし、この２つを合わせた重さは
Actually not many
実際には多くはありません
If we list all the percentages
すべての割合を列挙すると
You can see the darker, black piece over here
ここにもっと暗い黒い部分が見えます
We now call it dark energy
今ではそれをダークエネルギーと呼んでいます
In other words don't know what kind of energy it is
つまり、それがどんなエネルギーなのか分からない
Then here is the lighter black piece
次に、こちらが明るい黒色の部分です
is dark matter 30% 65%
暗黒物質は 30% 65%
Together it makes up 95% of the universe
合わせて宇宙の 95% を構成します
That is 95% of the universe
それは宇宙の95%です
we don't know what it is
それが何なのか私たちには分かりません
What we really know about Qing and Hari
チンとハリについて私たちが本当に知っていること
In terms of the scope it occupies
それが占める範囲に関しては
It's actually a very small part
それは実際には非常に小さな部分です
Of course there are some other elements that are less than Qinghe Harm
もちろん、清河害よりも劣る要素は他にもいくつかあります。
Let's look at it from here
ここから見てみましょう
If you look at it, the part with the most cloud heads in the universe is called green
見てみると、宇宙で一番雲頭が多い部分が緑と呼ばれています
Blue accounts for 60% and black accounts for 36% or 37%
青が60%、黒が36%または37%
Together it exceeds 95%
合わせると95%を超える
But this 95% is a relatively small amount in terms of the entire cosmic cloud head
しかし、この95％は宇宙の雲頭全体からすると比較的少ない量です。
Of course, the other part of us is not the same as on the earth.
もちろん、私たちの他の部分は地球上と同じではありません。
The most abundant part of the earth is actually iron
地球上で最も豊富な部分は実は鉄です
But most of the iron is in the center of the earth, not in the crust
しかし、鉄の大部分は地殻ではなく地球の中心にあります
If you look at it from the inside of the earth's crust
地殻の内側から見ると
Its most part should be oxygen and then fine
その大部分は酸素であり、その後は大丈夫であるはずです
These are all different elements, which is what you must know when you study chemistry.
これらはすべて異なる元素であり、化学を勉強するときに知っておく必要があります。
But because there is a lot of water in our living body, more than 75% is water
しかし、私たちの体の中には水分が多く存在しており、75％以上が水分です。
So you see, 65% is oxygen, and other words, blue accounts for 10%
つまり、65% が酸素、つまり緑が 10% を占めています。
So this together is mostly water
つまり、これはほとんどが水です
But our body contains a lot of carbon
しかし、私たちの体には炭素がたくさん含まれています
So it means the part we are most familiar with
つまり、私たちが最もよく知っている部分を意味します
Including ourselves, including the earth we live on
自分自身も含めて、私たちが住んでいる地球も含めて
Everything is completely different from the environment outside our earth.
地球外の環境とは何もかもが全く異なります。
Of course, if we look at it from the perspective of the entire universe
もちろん宇宙全体で見れば
We just said the transition from energy to matter
先ほどエネルギーから物質への移行について述べました
In fact, physicists are still spending a lot of effort to understand this process
実際、物理学者はこのプロセスを理解するために今でも多大な努力を費やしています。
However, there are some gradually more evidences showing that
しかし、それを示す証拠が徐々に増えてきています。
There are actually a lot of clouds in Cosmos
コスモスには実は雲がたくさんあるんです
it actually has mass
実際には質量がある
A phenomenon common to all matter is that it has mass
すべての物質に共通する現象は、物質には質量があるということです。
large or small mass
大きな塊または小さな塊
Although it is a small thing
小さなことですが
If it's a lot, it still has a lot of gravity
量が多ければ、それでも重力は大きい
It can be regarded as internal attraction, after being greedy and shrinking, it will produce scars
内なる魅力とも言える 貪欲で縮こまって傷跡を生む
Therefore, a circle mark heart actually undergoes greed and shrinkage.
したがって、丸印の心は実際に貪欲で縮みます。
it may become a scar
傷跡になるかもしれない
But there are big and small scars
でも大小の傷はあります
If you look at it from the heart
心から見れば
At its center, what actually happens is a nuclear reaction.
その中心で実際に起こるのは核反応です。
One of the two types of nuclear reactions is nuclear fission
2種類の核反応のうちの1つは核分裂です
A kind of nuclear fusion
核融合の一種
In fact it is because its content is mostly hydrogen
実はその成分のほとんどが水素だからです
So it's hydrogen atoms that produce nuclear fusion
つまり、核融合を起こすのは水素原子です
will form elements that slowly become comparisons
ゆっくりと比較される要素が形成されます
If the star is big enough
星が十分に大きかったら
It goes through nuclear fusion like this
このように核融合が起こります
Over time it will become a red giant star
やがて赤色巨星になる
The red giant is actually at the end
赤色巨星は実は終わりに近づいている
Its nuclear burn is very fast
核の燃焼が非常に速い
after such a rapid burn
このような急速な火傷の後
produces a lot of heavier elements
より重い元素が大量に生成される
when it dies
それが死ぬとき
there was a big bang
ビッグバンがあった
Such explosions could produce superstars
このような爆発はスーパースターを生み出す可能性がある
After this kind of superstar disperses the new elements around
この種のスーパースターが新しい要素を周囲にばら撒いた後、
It may again form a new solar system
再び新しい太陽系を形成する可能性がある
this is endless
それは終わりがない
But if it is a smaller star
でもそれがもっと小さな星だったら
when it has no chance of forming a red giant
赤色巨星を形成する機会がないとき
as soon as it goes to become a white dwarf
白色矮星になるとすぐに
so in fact
だから実際のところ
The ending may be different
結末は違うかもしれない
This is not my own professional field
これは私自身の専門分野ではありません
But at least we can see a new sun every day
でも少なくとも私たちは毎日新しい太陽を見ることができる
So when stars are in billions of years
つまり、星が数十億年後に存在するとき
Our sun is actually five billion years old
私たちの太陽は実際には50億歳です
lifespan of about five billion years
寿命は約50億年
This lifespan is very close to the lifespan of the earth
この寿命は地球の寿命に非常に近い
Earth's lifespan is currently estimated at 4.6 billion years
地球の寿命は現在46億年と推定されています
It is estimated that our sun should have another five billion years to survive
私たちの太陽はあと50億年生存できると推定されています
So the earth doesn't actually have to worry about the sun's last time
つまり、地球は太陽が最後に消滅するかどうかを心配する必要はありません。
Our sun will finally become a red giant star
私たちの太陽はついに赤色巨星になる
Then the words of the leader throughout the planetary system
そして惑星系全体のリーダーの言葉
It is probably light and harmful is the main
おそらく軽くて有害なものがメインです
But the other one percent is other elements
しかし、残りの1パーセントは他の要素です
This is so important to us
これは私たちにとってとても重要です
because few things seem
物事がほとんどないようなので
Instead, the rarest things around us
代わりに、私たちの周りにある最も珍しいもの
let's take a look
見てみましょう
Let's go back and look at the previous one just now
戻って前のものを見てみましょう
The last point is actually right
最後の点は実際には正しいです
It was rice ear swallow 200 years ago
200年前は稲穂ツバメだった
it raises an important concept
それは重要な概念を提起します
Because we just mentioned the name of the element
要素の名前を述べたばかりなので、
In fact every element
実はあらゆる要素が
Its units are atoms
その単位は原子です
Then if you have the same elements
次に、同じ要素がある場合
its atoms are the same
その原子は同じです
You if the elements are different
要素が違うと
its atoms are different words
その原子は別の言葉です
This is what we started in middle school
これは私たちが中学生のときに始めたものです
Atomic Blade
アトミックブレード
is what's inside
中にあるものは何ですか
things like this
このようなもの
when already looking out
すでに外を見ているとき
Kiss is indeed the most swallowed element in the universe
キスは確かに宇宙で最も飲み込まれた要素です
Although we say that there are many things
色々あるとは言いつつも
something that is not an element
要素ではないもの
The proportion is quite high
割合はかなり高いです
But if the already known elements swallow their heads
しかし、すでに知られている要素が彼らの頭を飲み込んだ場合、
Kiss is still the most content
やはりキスが一番内容が濃いですね
At the same time it is also persevering
それは同時に忍耐力でもあります
main ingredient
主成分
I'm taking this time to tell you about this
このことについてお話しするために時間を割いています
It is to let everyone experience one thing
みんなに一つのことを体験してもらうことです
between energy and matter
エネルギーと物質の間
The relationship is actually very close
実はその関係はとても親密なのです
What kind of environmental conditions is the problem
どのような環境条件が問題なのか
such as temperature or
気温や
Kinetic energy of matter itself
物質そのものの運動エネルギー
enabling them to move between pools and people
プールと人間の間を移動できるようにする
mutual change
相互変化
In fact, speaking of chemistry
実は化学と言えば
change between energy and matter
エネルギーと物質の間で変化する
it has very specific rules
非常に具体的なルールがある
For example, if you look at it like a blue atom
たとえば、青い原子のように見ると
It has only one Naoko in the center
中心には直子が一人だけいる
There will be an electron outside
外には電子があるでしょう
So we say that the blue atom has a direct son
したがって、青い原子には直接の息子がいると言います
and an electron
そして電子
but above the sun
でも太陽の上では
its son
その息子
Two pairs of sons will be fused
二組の息子が融合します
in the process of fusion
融合の過程で
and many smaller examples
および多くの小さな例
For example, neutrinos
例えばニュートリノ
Zhengzi
正子啊
A positron is the opposite of an electron
陽電子は電子の反対です
The quality is the same as that of electrons
電子と同じ品質です
But electricity and electrons are just the opposite
でも電気と電子は逆です
It's on standby
スタンバイ中です
put something like this out
このようなものを出します
then it will generate
そうすれば生成されます
Naoko
直子
but neutrons
しかし中性子
After Naoko and Naoko got together
直子と直子が付き合ってから
it has the opportunity to generate new elements
新しい要素を生成する機会があります
so keep going down
だからずっと下がってください
it becomes a practiced display
練習用の表示になります
go down
降りる
It can even release Gama rays
ガマ線も放つことができる
so straight out
とてもストレートに
and then into a new substance
そして新しい物質に
It can be harmful in the end
最終的には有害になる可能性があります
That is, throughout the development process
つまり、開発プロセス全体を通じて、
Although not achieved in one step
一歩で達成できなくても
But in the end we know that the sun is
しかし最終的に私たちは太陽が
Constant consumption is kinder
継続的に消費する方が優しい
Shouldn't it be kind, should it be pro-atomic?
親切であるべきではなく、原子力推進であるべきなのでしょうか？
then produce harmful atoms
その後、有害な原子が生成されます
But there are other ways, dear, there are actually two
でも他の方法もありますよ、実際には 2 つあります
That is to say it has a finger
つまり指があるということ
So it's a kiss but with a middle finger at the same time
つまりキスだけど同時に中指を立てて
This is what we call a knife
これが私たちがナイフと呼ぶものです
There is also a pointing
指差しも
then there are two middle fingers
それから中指は2本です
As long as you have one pointing finger, it belongs to the relatives anyway.
あなたが人差し指を一本持っている限り、それはとにかく親戚のものです。
belonging to the same number of relatives
同数の親族に属する
If these two things collide
この二つが衝突すると
It can also produce a harmful atom
有害な原子も生成する可能性がある
Contains two middle fingers and two fingers
中指2本と指2本が入っています
That is, we can write it in chemical formula
つまり化学式で書くと
it can be harmful and
それは有害である可能性があり、
Situations like this happen every day
このような状況は毎日のように起こります
it happens on the sun
それは太陽で起こる
But in the part of its comparison
しかし、その比較の部分では
In fact there are some heavier elements
実際にはもっと重い要素がいくつかあります
the heaviest sinks in the middle
最も重いものは真ん中に沈みます
very little
とても少ない
But most of them are outside
でもほとんどが外にいる
Layer by layer, according to its density
密度に応じて層ごとに
can be distinguished
区別できる
So it can actually produce eggs
それで実際に卵を産むことができる
can produce oxygen
酸素を生成できる
So we just mentioned
それで、先ほども述べましたが、
words at the center of the star
星の中心にある言葉
If you go through nuclear fusion continuously
核融合を続けていくと
heavy elements will occur
重元素が発生する
So for example like a carbon atom
たとえば炭素原子のように
like nitrogen atom
窒素原子のような
In fact, if we continue to integrate
実際、統合を続けると、
nitrogen atom followed by hydrogen atom
窒素原子、続いて水素原子
Fusion into oxygen atoms
酸素原子への融合
So keep it up and you'll find
だからそれを続けてください、そうすれば見つかります
It has new elements coming out all the time
新しい要素がどんどん出てくるので
see it this way
こうやって見てください
our solar system
私たちの太陽系
should have been
になるはずだった
A sun has already exploded
太陽はすでに爆発した
into a super new system
超新システムに
and re-transform into one of our planetary systems
そして私たちの惑星系の一つに再変換されました
It should be so
そうあるべきだ
so in this
それでこれで
the mystery of its energy
そのエネルギーの謎
just press
押すだけ
proposed
提案された
If you have to sacrifice a little material quality
素材の品質を少し犠牲にする必要がある場合
to generate energy
エネルギーを生成する
its often tiny mass
多くの場合、その塊は小さい
multiply by the speed of light
光の速度を掛ける
That is, the square of an astronomical number
つまり天文学的な数の二乗
make it produce huge lotus kernels
巨大な蓮の実を生産させます
This kind of energy is very large
この種のエネルギーは非常に大きいです
but so far
しかし、これまでのところ
Humans have not yet been able to take full advantage of
人類はまだその恩恵を十分に活用できていない
other than using it as a bomb
爆弾として使う以外に
there seems to be no good way
良い方法はないようです
take full advantage of
最大限に活用する
But in the US and in the UK
でもアメリカやイギリスでは
There are some cohesive atomic furnaces
いくつかの凝集型原子炉があります
are doing experimental research
実験研究を行っています
hope to find
見つかることを願っています
can we replace
交換できますか
Now new personnel come to use
新しい人材が活躍するようになりました
Except for the case of the sun
太陽の場合を除いて
It also emits what we call light
また、私たちが光と呼ぶものを発します
what is light
光とは何ですか
In fact, from a more scientific point of view,
実際、より科学的な観点から見ると、
The stars are actually emitting battery radiation
星は実際にバッテリー放射線を放出しています
In fact, it is a dose of radiation
実はそれは放射線量です
The amount of radiation
放射線量
what we call light
私たちが光と呼ぶもの
The reason is because in all its range
その理由は、すべての範囲で
quite a while
かなり長い間
We human eyes can see
私たち人間の目は見ることができます
call it visible light
それを可視光と呼ぶ
In the shorter wavelength part of visible light
可視光の短波長部分では
and the longer part of the words
そして単語の長い部分
we have some names
私たちにはいくつかの名前があります
Some of the names are familiar
中にはおなじみの名前もあります
For example, the possibility of relative cosmic color lines
たとえば、相対的な宇宙の色線の可能性
Gamma color line because now the brain
ガンマカラーラインは今脳だから
If there is a flow knife
フローナイフがあれば
We say Gamma knife refers to Gamma color line
ガンマナイフとはガンマカラーラインのことを指します
Then the X-ray is from Professor Wang Yu.
そして、レントゲンは王宇教授からのものです。
research expertise
研究の専門知識
Then at the wavelength towards
次に、次の波長で
words here
ここの言葉
stick to visible light
可視光線にこだわる
The shorter wavelength on the left is ultraviolet light
左側の短い波長が紫外線です
Infrared rays with longer wavelengths
より波長の長い赤外線
if you go down
下がったら
microwaves are radio waves
マイクロ波は電波です
It's all familiar to everyone.
それは誰もがよく知っていることです。
In this posture
この姿勢に関して言えば、
We call it photoreplenishment
私たちはそれを光補充と呼んでいます
this is gossip
これはゴシップです
what does it teach us
それは私たちに何を教えてくれますか
we just said
私たちは今言いました
Scientists must have a special scope
科学者は特別な範囲を持たなければなりません
to see special targets
特別なターゲットを確認するには
the same reason
同じ理由
Spectroscopy also allows us to see
分光法を使えば見ることもできます
We use different wavelengths
私たちは異なる波長を使用します
Or if you look at it with frequency light
あるいは周波数光で見ると
We can see inside matter
物質の内部が見える
different phenomena
さまざまな現象
don't go into detail about what kind of phenomenon
どのような現象かについては詳しく述べないでください
But these different phenomena
しかし、これらのさまざまな現象は、
In fact, it allows us to have new perspectives and perspectives
実際、それは私たちに新しい視点や視点を持つことを可能にします
say again
もう一回言って
Tell us the tool should be right
ツールが適切であることを教えてください
And look for the right direction
そして正しい方向を探してください
as if you see
まるで見ているかのように
if you want to watch desktop
デスクトップを見たい場合は
I probably wouldn't intentionally switch to a Chinese-style channel.
おそらく意図的に中国風のチャンネルに切り替えることはないだろう。
So I just have to see desktops on that channel
したがって、そのチャネル上のデスクトップを表示するだけで済みます
then we will never see
そうすれば私たちは決して見ることはできません
The reason is very simple
理由はとても簡単です
Another form of energy deserves our attention
別の形態のエネルギーも注目に値します
chemical energy
化学エネルギー
This is especially true on Earth
これは特に地球に当てはまります
more noticeable energy
より顕著なエネルギー
We just said that the interaction of functions
先ほど関数の相互作用について述べました。
Most of the aforementioned nuclear energy
前述の原子力エネルギーのほとんどは、
But when matter is formed
しかし、物質が形成されるとき、
often release energy
エネルギーを放出することが多い
if it is destroyed
それが破壊された場合
often absorb energy
エネルギーを吸収することが多い
In fact, if we put it in more precise terms
実際、もっと正確に言うと
From your chemist's point of view
化学者の観点から
It should be about atoms bonded together
それは結合した原子に関するものでなければなりません
if you pull it out
それを引き出せば
You have to give it its full amount
全額を与えなければなりません
If the separated atoms
原子が分離した場合
if you want to tie it together
それを結びつけたければ
it will surely let people out
それはきっと人々を外へ出すだろう
This is from a scientist's point of view
これは科学者の観点からの話です
is a rule like this
こんなルールです
If we use this picture to see
この写真を使って見てみると
If this axis is the original quantity
この軸が元の量の場合
If this axis is the distance between atoms
この軸を原子間の距離とすると
You will find that when you put two pro-atoms
2つのプロ原子を置くとそれがわかります
let it get closer
近づけさせてください
Its original volume is to go to the bottom
本来のボリュームは一番下に行きます
and when you go to the lowest place
そして一番低いところに行くと
Logically, it is the most stable place
論理的にはそれが最も安定した場所です
That is, many middle school students here
つまり、ここには中学生がたくさんいます
What you learned in middle school or high school failed
中学や高校で習ったことは失敗した
also failed at the lowest time
最低の時間でも失敗した
it should be most stable
それが最も安定するはずです
But if you let it get closer
でも近づけば
electron and atom box inside it
その中の電子と原子の箱
there is power
力がある
so it deliberately pushes them back apart
だから意図的にそれらを引き離すのです
So the number will rise again
それでまた数字が上がるだろう
So probably when stable
だからおそらく安定しているときは
it's all within this range
すべてこの範囲内です
So its distance has a stable range
そのため、その距離は安定した範囲を持っています
Of course if you give it energy
もちろんエネルギーを与えれば
let it climb
登らせてください
Just like we need energy to climb a mountain
山に登るのにエネルギーが必要なのと同じように
Let it go when the distance gets farther and farther
距離がどんどん遠くなっていくときは手放して
you can take it apart
分解できます
So chemical energy is what makes matter
つまり、化学エネルギーが物質を作るのです
when forming and breaking
形成時と破壊時
The number of people incidental to the change
変更に伴う人数
At this time there will be a
このとき、
Scientists have two perspectives to see things
科学者は物事を見るために 2 つの視点を持っています
If you consider matter as the subject
物質を主体として考えると
you will find
見つけるだろう
The substance is changing its form
物質は形を変えていく
For example, the atoms I just mentioned
たとえば、先ほど述べた原子
when combined
組み合わせると
or when separated
または別れるとき
or when new substances are formed
または新しい物質が形成されるとき
when rearranging
並べ替えるとき
it will have to come in or go out with the energy
エネルギーが入ってくるか出ていく必要があります
So as if matter is the subject
あたかも物質が主題であるかのように
energy is class
エネルギーは階級です
energy goes out
エネルギーが抜けていく
But you also have another way to see it
しかし、別の見方もできます
regard energy as subject
エネルギーを主体として考える
And if we regard the matter as a subject
そして、この問題を主題として考えると、
When energy changes from high to low in that place
その場所のエネルギーが高い状態から低い状態に変化するとき
Matter follows, so we have to accept a little more energy
問題はその後に続くので、もう少しエネルギーを受け入れなければなりません
If it receives less energy, its shape will change back and forth
受けるエネルギーが少なくなると、その形状は前後に変化します。
So watch your goals look at energy
だから、目標に気をつけて、エネルギーに注目してください
still look at the material
まだ資料を見てください
All in all, a very basic concept
全体として、非常に基本的な概念です
Not just nuclear energy or chemical energy
原子力や化学エネルギーだけではない
its different sizes
さまざまなサイズ
But it will be accompanied by changes in matter
しかしそれには事態の変化も伴うだろう
This is the most important point
これが最も重要なポイントです
if you don't study science
科学を勉強しないと
At least you know that energy is always following the change of matter
少なくとも、エネルギーは常に物質の変化に従っていることを知っています。
on our planet, especially
私たちの地球上では、特に
In the top of the air, there are many small molecules
空気の上には小さな分子がたくさんあります
For example, oxygen is familiar to everyone
例えば、酸素は誰にとっても身近なものです。
That carbon dioxide is what everyone hates
二酸化炭素は誰もが嫌うものです
Carbon dioxide, everyone is afraid of hearing it now
二酸化炭素、今は誰もがそれを聞くのを恐れています
then carbon dioxide
それから二酸化炭素
Carbon dioxide is also poisonous
二酸化炭素も有毒です
But in our body
しかし私たちの体の中では
It is very important for nerve conduction
神経伝導にとって非常に重要です
Holiday night can be regarded as
休日の夜は次のように考えることができます
gas to burn
燃焼するガス
Peace of mind
心の平和
or sulfur dioxide
または二酸化硫黄
So you will find that there are many substances
そうすると物質がたくさんあることがわかります
Can be spread in our atmospheric city
雰囲気のある街に広がる
by us
我々によって
increasingly familiar substances
ますます身近な物質
I was very familiar with matter when I didn't know science before
以前科学を知らなかったとき、私は物質について非常に精通していました
like this
このような
it side
それ側
blue is
青は
Green molecules
青分子
red oxygen molecule
赤い酸素分子
and after you burn it
そしてそれを燃やした後
it can combine into water molecules
それは水分子に結合することができます
So this one that looks like Mickey Mouse's head
これはミッキーマウスの頭のように見えます
with two ears
両耳付き
water molecules
水の分子
other small molecules
他の小分子
I won't go into detail
詳細には触れません
but macromolecules
しかし高分子
like our genetics
私たちの遺伝子のように
this
これ
genetic code
遺伝コード
Responsible DNA
責任あるDNA
its atoms
その原子
The atoms in a molecule are at least
分子内の原子は少なくとも
more than a thousand
上千以上
so you can tell
だからあなたは言うことができます
At least hundreds of thousands of atoms
少なくとも数十万個の原子
is very large
とても大きいです
so simple
とても簡単
Whether it is a simple molecule or a complex molecule
単純な分子か複雑な分子か
This is what caused our earth
これが私たちの地球の原因です
One of the most basic reasons why its landscape is so diverse
この地域の景観が非常に多様である最も基本的な理由の 1 つは、
So we say that when the sun uses electromagnetic radiation
したがって、太陽が電磁放射を使用すると、
It is far from feeling that the energy is sent to the planet
エネルギーが地球に送られているという実感とは程遠い
The matter on the planet because of the incoming energy
入ってくるエネルギーによって地球上に問題が発生
it can start to change
それは変わり始めるかもしれない
This is the change between people and matter that I just emphasized again and again
これが私が繰り返し強調した人と物質の間の変化です
Nature begins with nuclear energy and head and chemical energy and head
自然は核エネルギーと頭、化学エネルギーと頭から始まる
Transformed its matter and created our world
物質を変化させて私たちの世界を創造した
One of them is that everyone often
そのうちの 1 つは、誰もがよくあることです。
Even in recent years, students often hear
近年でも学生さんからよく聞かれるのが、
What you often see in the newspapers is the greenhouse effect
新聞でよく目にするのは温室効果です
The greenhouse effect is what I just said
温室効果とは今言ったことです
Often when the media introduces them inaccurately
メディアが不正確に紹介する場合が多い
Now quite a lot of people are scared when they hear about the greenhouse effect
今、かなり多くの人が温室効果について聞くと怖がります
Think that the greenhouse effect after the increase of carbon dioxide
二酸化炭素の増加後の温室効果を考える
will make our temperature higher and higher
私たちの体温はどんどん上がっていきます
Then we just get sadder and sadder
それから私たちはますます悲しくなるだけです
And it's causing big changes in the climate
そしてそれは気候に大きな変化を引き起こしています
Count all the burials on it
そこにあるすべての埋葬物を数えてください
In fact, the greenhouse effect is harmful to the ability of human beings to live in this world.
実際、温室効果は人間がこの世界で生きていく能力に有害です。
A very important life-saving effect
非常に重要な救命効果
Because when the sun shines radiation on the earth,
なぜなら、太陽が地球に放射線を当てると、
it will reflect back
それは反射して戻ってきます
after reflecting back
反省してから
There are actually some molecules in the top of the atmosphere here.
ここの大気の上部には実際にいくつかの分子があります。
Putting it in the atmosphere can reflect it back
大気中に置くと反射する可能性があります
So look at the picture below
それで、下の写真を見てください
It is easier for everyone to understand
誰にとっても理解しやすくなります
Infrared rays actually affect the greenhouse effect
赤外線は実際に温室効果に影響を与えます
The most critical radiation dose
最も重要な放射線量
It's because of incoming radiation
放射線が入ってくるからだよ
when reflected
反射したとき
it doesn't all go out
全部出なくなるわけではない
it's blocked by some gas and put back
ガスによってブロックされ、元に戻されてしまう
some infrared light here
ここに赤外線がいくつかあります
is actually what keeps our planet warm
実は私たちの地球を暖かく保っているのです
actually very gentle
実はとても優しい
Why do we say that the temperature of the earth is very mild?
なぜ地球の気温は非常に穏やかだと言えるのでしょうか?
because the surface of the sun
なぜなら太陽の表面は
should not say it is the surface
それが表面であると言うべきではありません
this calendar
このカレンダー
It should be 6000 degrees C
6000℃になるはずです
Yes, if we want to encounter such an environment
そう、そんな環境に出会いたければ
we say dire straits
私たちは悲惨な状況だと言います
Probably our whole body is gasified
おそらく全身がガス化しているのだろう
impossible
不可能
If you go to read history
歴史を読みに行くなら
When Pompeii was covered by volcanoes
ポンペイが火山に覆われていた頃
When its hot air sweeps over people
その熱風が人々を覆う時
less than 6000 degrees
6000度未満
The temperature of thousands of degrees is already
すでに数千度の温度が
Everyone gasified and exploded.
全員がガス化して爆発した。
But if it's in the desert
でもそれが砂漠の中なら
The temperature is relatively high
気温が比較的高い
It may be higher than 40 degrees
40度以上になることもある
words from the rainforest
熱帯雨林からの言葉
Similar to today's Taipei
今の台北に似ています
35 degrees C
35度C
If Antarctica
南極なら
The average temperature can be maintained below zero
平均気温を氷点下に維持できる
The words of the ocean are in fact the hub of regulation
海の言葉は実際には規制の中心地である
the average temperature on Earth
地球上の平均気温
Should be around 15 degrees C
気温は15℃くらいになるはず
lowest words
最低な言葉
It's hard to get below -50 degrees C on earth
地球上では-50℃以下になるのは難しい
It's hard to be higher than 10 degrees C at noon
昼でも10℃を超えるのは厳しいですね
So it is relative to the scale of facilities
施設の規模に比例するので、
100 degrees C is not a very wide range
100℃というのはそれほど広い範囲ではありません
It's not like we don't talk about Mars today
今日は火星の話をしないわけではない
On Mars, 200 degrees C at night
火星では夜間は摂氏200度
It gets up to 400 degrees C during the day
日中は400℃まで上がります
This change is hundreds of degrees C
この変化は摂氏数百度です
so the difference can be huge
その違いは非常に大きくなる可能性があります
In addition to the atmosphere
雰囲気以外は
Other aspects of the crust can pay a little attention
地殻の他の側面にも少し注意を払うことができます
I can actually speed up this part a bit.
実はこの部分を少しスピードアップすることができます。
You will find that our earth is not a uniform sphere
私たちの地球は均一な球体ではないことがわかるでしょう
It has a core and a core that we call geochill
それにはコアとコアがあり、それをジオチルと呼んでいます
In fact, what we are most familiar with is actually the surface of the earth.
実は、私たちが最もよく知っているのは地球の表面です。
the part called the crust
地殻と呼ばれる部分
because it is a hard shape
硬い形状なので
Hard shape means we stand on it
硬い形状はその上に立つことを意味します
it is hard
それは難しい
not like jupiter
木星とは違います
We have four hard shapes which are Mercury, Venus, Mars and Earth
私たちには水星、金星、火星、地球という 4 つの具体的な形があります。
These four are hard shapes
この4つは難しい形状です
But others such as Jupiter
しかし、木星などの他の星は
Purus Uranus Neptune
普星 天王星 海王星
are gaseous planets
ガス惑星です
For a hard cross planet like this
このようなハードなクロスプラネットの場合
in terms of its entire structure
全体の構造的には
Earth Chill and Earth and Yes are in it
冷やして地面に置いて、はい、中にあります
It is obvious that the middle longitudinal density is high
中縦密度が高いのがわかります。
It's a little less dense here
ここは少し密度が低いです
outermost minimum
最外面最小
Indicates that chemistry has a
化学には
Chemical consonance means according to density
密度に応じた化学的調和の意味
Sink vertically Float upward gently
垂直に沈みます ゆっくりと上に浮き上がります
That's what I mean
それが私の言いたいことです
So roughly speaking
大雑把に言えば
The lightest density is probably outside the crust
最も軽い密度はおそらく地殻の外にあります
But in the part where the ground is cold
でも地面が冷たい部分では
it actually has some heat
実際にはある程度の熱を持っています
let out the heat
熱を外に出す
is to make it convective
対流させることです
convection phenomenon that is
対流現象、つまり
hot part
熱い部分
its density will be lower
その密度は低くなります
just run up
ただ駆け上がるだけ
Just like our air
私たちの空気のように
so don't look
だから見ないでください
Are you saying that this is not the lithosphere of soil rocks?
これは土壌岩のリソスフェアではないということですか？
it can still flow
まだ流れることができる
slow flow
ゆっくりとした流れ
So there is convection
それで対流が起こる
so when
そうするとき
words at the core
核となる言葉
It has no effect on the surface temperature
表面温度には影響しません
But for the convective part of the cold
しかし、寒さの対流部分に関しては
it may have an effect
影響があるかもしれない
especially if there is gas in it
特にガスが入っている場合
a class of explosive words
爆発的な単語のクラス
It might have erupted from a volcano.
火山から噴火したのかもしれない。
let's jump over
飛び越えてみましょう
So volcanoes are relative to the surface
したがって、火山は地表に対して相対的なものです
is a very important thing
とても重要なことです
We often say that the surface of the earth
私たちはよく「地球の表面」と言いますが、
is a living form
生きた形です
One of the very important reasons
非常に重要な理由の 1 つは
That is, we now have active volcanoes for everyone
つまり、誰もが利用できる活火山が存在するのです。
Still working on the surface
まだ表面上で作業中
Datun Mountain is a repair volcano
大屯山は修復火山です
On the face of it
表面的には
no very clear apparent activity
あまり明確な活動は見られない
But in fact judging from its flow prevention pit
しかし、実際には、流れ防止ピットから判断すると、
still working
まだ働いています
Maybe hundreds of years or a thousand years from now
おそらく今から数百年か千年後
It might explode again
また爆発するかもしれない
But in the Atlantic
しかし大西洋では
we can see an obvious
明らかなことがわかります
from the cold
寒さから
all the way to the surface
表面までずっと
it's because of the persistent heat
続いている暑さのせいです
Convection like this is maintained
このような対流が維持されます
Then the gas comes out
そうするとガスが出てきます
so that the bottom of the Atlantic Ocean
大西洋の底になるように
Expand to both sides
両側に展開する
so it has an atlantic level ditch
大西洋レベルの溝があります
still going on
まだ続いている
broadened process development
幅広いプロセス開発
still under development
まだ開発中です
So this magma its movement
このマグマの動きは
Earth's surface provided
地球の表面が提供される
very important vitality
とても大切な活力
We even say it is the vitality of construction
それは建設の活力だとさえ言われます
for example
例えば
Look carefully at the words of the Atlantic class
アトランティッククラスの言葉をよく見てください
it comes out warm sea water
温かい海水が出てきます
around this
このあたり
We used to think that in this hotter seawater
この熱い海水の中で私たちはこう思っていた
no living things
生き物がいない
now we find
今私たちは見つけました
In fact, at such a high temperature
実際、このような高温では、
There are still very special creatures
まだまだ特殊な生き物がいる
And it has good nutrients to grow
成長に良い栄養素も含まれているので、
So don't read that in this
だからこの記事ではそれを読まないでください
at such a high temperature
こんなに高い温度で
It is not easy to say that biological survival
生物学的に生き残ると言うのは簡単ではありません
In fact, organisms are very easy to adapt to the environment
実際、生物は環境に適応するのが非常に簡単です
So we have a saying here
そこで、ここで言いたいことがあります
The earth is like Athena in Greek mythology
地球はギリシャ神話のアテナのようなものです
It has both properties
両方の性質を持っています
It seems to have the wisdom of all things
万物の叡智を秘めているようだ
But on the other hand it also has a lot of violence
しかしその一方で暴力性も高い
You sometimes see disasters happening on Earth
地球上で災害が起こっているのを時々見かけます
key report
主要なレポート
The key report is that
重要なレポートは、
It's not that aliens are coming, it's that
宇宙人がやってくるのではなく、
Then there is something special
それから何か特別なものがあります
For example, Mr. Wang is going to run away somewhere to hide.
たとえば、王さんはどこかに逃げて隠れるつもりです。
From the point of view of scientists
科学者の観点から
nature is not particularly kind
自然は特別優しいわけではない
But it doesn't have to be particularly cruel
でも特に残酷である必要はない
most likely it manifests
おそらくそれが現れます
sometimes we feel indifferent
時々私たちは無関心に感じます
when its violence chokes some life
その暴力が誰かの命を窒息させるとき
we sometimes think it's cold
私たちは時々寒いと思うことがあります
But when it is experienced in all things
しかし、それがすべてのことにおいて経験されるとき、
We think it's actually full of cancer
実際は癌だらけだと思う
That's why the Greeks called it Mother Earth
だからこそギリシャ人はそれを「母なる地球」と呼んだのです
In the process of the development of the earth I just said that we have
地球の発展の過程で、私たちは、
about 4.6 billion years ago
約46億年前
The scale actually makes it very wide
スケールは実際には非常に広いです
If it's 4.6 billion years here
ここが46億年なら
That's 4 billion years
それは40億年です
So here it is 2.1 billion years
つまりこれは21億年です
1.1 billion years here
ここで11億年
500 million years here
ここで5億年
If we look a little closer
もう少し近づいて見てみると
earliest stone found
最古の石が発見された
approximately over 4 billion years
約40億年以上
is a stone found in Australia
オーストラリアで見つかった石です
you will find
見つけるだろう
1984 is very close to now
1984年距離現在時間非常的近
But about 30 years
でも30年くらい
ingredients in it
その中の成分
In fact, using the current single catty analysis
実際、現在の 1 斤分析を使用すると、
can already be seen
すでに見えています
you can clearly see
はっきりとわかります
It has two metal atoms in it
金属原子が2つ入っている
one is high
一つは高い
one is young
一人は若いです
In other words, of course, there are sheep
つまり、羊ももちろんいます。
So we already know the ingredients
つまり、成分はすでにわかっています
stone like this
このような石
it's actually igneous rock
実は火成岩です
was produced at a very early age
非常に早い時期に生み出された
except this
これを除いて
there are still some very old rocks on earth
地球上にはまだ非常に古い岩石がいくつかあります
For example, it was discovered in Canada in the 1940s
たとえば、1940年代にカナダで発見されました。
It is in fact in Greenland, Iceland, probably
それは実際には、おそらくアイスランドのグリーンランドにあります
Earlier rocks were found in that area
その地域では以前に石が発見されました
Also some bacteria
いくつかの細菌も
Of course, this bacterium is no longer a living bacterium.
もちろん、この細菌はもはや生きた細菌ではありません。
actually a fossil
実は化石
So judging by its size
なので、その大きさから判断すると、
Very likely a fossil of bacteria
細菌の化石の可能性が高い
Its size is actually only 10 to 20
そのサイズは実際にはわずか10〜20個です
We can only do micron
ミクロンしかできない
That's 10 belly fat
お腹の脂肪は10個分です
It was discovered more than 30 years ago
30年以上前に発見された
In other words, the earliest life on earth
つまり、地球上で最も古い生命体は、
Probably more than 30 years from now
おそらく今から30年以上先になるでしょう
the length of time
時間の長さ
I have a lot of this time scale today
今日はこの時間スケールがたくさんあります
tell everyone
みんなに言ってください
I am slowly
私はゆっくりです
accumulated from reading different books
さまざまな本を読んで蓄積された
So now I'm getting more and more familiar with this time scale.
それで今、私はこの時間スケールにますます慣れてきました。
if you don't often hear
あまり聞かないなら
Maybe it will be a little uncomfortable for a while
しばらくは少し不便になるかもしれません
35 years is very long
35年って本当に長いですね
Are some people not even 35 yet?
まだ35歳にもなってない人もいるの？
Is it right
そうですか
If it's bacteria, let it
細菌なら放っておいてください
It should mean that the cell wants it to
それは細胞がそれを望んでいることを意味するはずです
It is more special if it contains the nucleus
核が入っているとさらに特別です
In fact, it's been almost a billion years.
実際、それは約10億年かかります。
We are about 12 years old
私たちは約12歳です
The present plant with a nucleus
核を持った現在の植物
It's almost 12 years now
もう12年近く経つのですね
A very important thing happened in the middle
途中でとても重要なことが起こりました
That is, when it is almost 21 years away
つまり、もう21年も経つと、
Oxygen begins to be produced in large quantities on Earth
地球上で酸素が大量に生成され始める
Indicates that the earth was in the early days
地球が原始の時代にあったことを示す
without as much oxygen as we have now
今ほど多くの酸素がないと
So if there are other bacteria present at that time
したがって、その時点で他の細菌が存在している場合は、
It doesn't live on oxygen
酸素を食べて生きているわけではない
eukaryotic cells for more than ten years
真核細胞は10年以上
really more like
本当にもっと好きです
We look more like animals
私たちはもっと動物に似ています
It's been around 500 million years
5億年ほど経ちました
Many people, especially children, know
多くの人、特に子供たちは知っています
Reptiles were around 200 million years ago
爬虫類は約2億年前に存在した
Just climbed from Mercury Head to the road
マーキュリーヘッドから道路まで登ったところです
Because when reptiles appear
爬虫類が出てくると
Dinosaurs also appeared
恐竜も登場
So we look at it through the eyes of a chemist
そこで私たちは化学者の目を通してそれを見ていきます
The most important life is to be able to survive
人生で最も大切なことは生き延びることです
That is to say, energy must come into it from the outside world.
つまり、外界からエネルギーが入ってくる必要があります。
It is likely to flow into its body in the form of matter
物質の形で体内に流入する可能性が高い
But when you go in, you have to generate energy
しかし、中に入るときはエネルギーを生成する必要があります
make it work with energy
エネルギーを使って機能させる
this is any kind of life
これはどんな人生でもある
no matter what form it is
それがどんな形であっても
We are also good
私たちもいいよ
or the smallest cell
または最小の細胞
or bacteria
または細菌
should have such conditions
そのような条件があるはずです
We just talked about the time from 21 to 31 years
先ほど21歳から31歳までのことを話しました。
In fact, some photosynthetic life has appeared
実は光合成生命も出現している
In fact, you can now see blue-green algae
実際、今では藍藻が見られるようになりました
Also it forms such cells
また、そのような細胞を形成します
In fact the first thing you see
実際、最初に目にするものは
is green
緑の
Everyone knows that green is because of the leaves of green trees.
緑は緑の木の葉のおかげであることは誰もが知っています。
This picture is actually a chemist who wants to spend
この写真は実際にお金を使いたい化学者です
A picture that took a long time to understand
理解するのに時間がかかった絵
There are still many things in it that we can't understand
その中にはまだ理解できないことがたくさんある
But at least everyone learned it in middle school
でも少なくとも誰もが中学校で習った
If you take water and crocodile carbon as raw materials
水とクロコダイルカーボンを原料とする場合
put the cells in the leaves to lead
細胞を葉の中に入れてリードする
Relying on chlorophyll plus light, it is called photosynthesis
クロロフィルと光を頼りに行うことを光合成といいます
it produces oxygen and glucose
酸素とブドウ糖を生成します
Symptoms actually have a very complicated operation of the number of people
症状は実際には非常に複雑な人数の操作を行っています
And the operation of this human quantity it goes from plant to animal
そしてこの人間の量の働きは植物から動物へと伝わります
have a similar mechanism at work
同様のメカニズムが働いている
Our so-called ADP ATP is actually called
私たちのいわゆる ADP ATP は、実際には
Dilingic acid is a kind of plum is a kind of enzyme
ジリンギ酸はプラムの一種で酵素の一種です
ATP is Mitsubishi acid
ATPは三菱酸です
Alteration of trees by rhombic acid
菱形酸による樹木の変質
After making its chemical reaction happen
化学反応を起こした後
There are changes in energy
エネルギーに変化が起こる
At the same time, if there is another breathing effect here
同時に、ここに別の呼吸効果がある場合
Of course our bodies rely on oxygen to burn
もちろん、私たちの体は酸素に依存して燃焼しています
Provide energy for the functioning of our body
私たちの体の機能にエネルギーを供給します
So glucose can be used as fuel here
つまり、グルコースはここで燃料として使用できます
So the two big cycles are chemically
したがって、2 つの大きなサイクルは化学的には
is very important
はとても重要です
Using chemistry to exchange between matter and energy
化学を利用して物質とエネルギーを交換する
make our lives work
私たちの生活をうまく機能させる
this is a very important thing
これはとても重要なことです
But if we look at it from a historical perspective
しかし、歴史的な観点から見てみると、
We were just talking about half a billion years ago
私たちはちょうど5億年前のことについて話していました
In fact, there are a lot of special creatures appearing
実は特殊な生き物がたくさん登場するんです
Let's see the next one will be more clear
次はもっと明確になるでしょう
This time is about 500 million years
この時間は約5億年です
It's called Han Wuji
ハン・ウージといいます
If you go to the Canadian Rockies
カナディアンロッキーに行くなら
look up
見上げる
Or if you go to see it in China's Yunnan and Guangxi areas
あるいは中国の雲南省や広西チワン族自治区に見に行ったら
You can find words like this
こんな言葉も見つかります
It can be seen as an animal
動物のようにも見える
Because it's not like a lobster, it's like a cockroach
ロブスターじゃなくてゴキブリみたいだから
But now on earth
でも今地球上では
you can't find it anywhere
どこにも見つかりません
because almost the vast majority of
なぜなら、ほぼ大多数の
They're all extinct
それらはすべて絶滅した
it's almost in han wu ji
もうすぐ漢武記です
That is, 500 million years from now
つまり5億年後
It's all of a sudden gone extinct
いつの間にか絶滅してしまった
after extinction
絶滅後
Many fossils are left in the marble
大理石の中に多くの化石が残されている
inside the rock formation
岩層の内部
So when I just said that in Luojishan and
それで、カナダの羅鶏山と羅鶏山について言ったとき
Southern part of mainland China
中国本土南部
can see
見える
But you now because it is a hard-shelled animal
でもあなたは今、殻の固い動物だから
So after you dug it out
それで、それを掘り出した後、
You find that its shape is still in that place
その形がまだその場所に残っていることがわかります
But when these creatures suddenly a large number
しかし、これらの生き物が突然大量に増えたとき、
dead when extinct
絶滅したら死ぬ
there is a very interesting thing
とても興味深いことがあります
between 500 million and 200 million years
5億年から2億年の間
there are very fast
非常に速いものがあります
Haiying head creatures are also good
ハイインヘッドのクリーチャーも良いですね
and creatures that walk on the ground
そして地面を歩く生き物たち
rapid development
急速な発展
What does this mean?
これは何を意味するのでしょうか？
when the environment is right
環境が整っているとき
some creatures are lost
いくつかの生き物が失われている
its chance of survival
その生存の可能性
Other creatures suddenly
他の生き物が突然
get its chance of survival
生き残るチャンスを得る
In other words, what we now call the exchange of ecological blocks
言い換えれば、現在私たちが生態学的ブロックの交換と呼んでいるものです。
Because if you give up your position
自分の立場を放棄したら
Then I'll sit down so the wind blows
それから風が吹くように座ります
So the earth is actually doing destructive creation again and again
つまり地球は実際に破壊的な創造を繰り返しているのです
Just like the volcano I just mentioned
先ほど言った火山のように
natural disasters on our earth
私たちの地球上の自然災害
It's been decades
何十年も経ちました
never disappeared
決して消えなかった
we can talk so much today
今日はたくさん話せます
like taiwan
台湾のように
Every year when a typhoon comes, we will be nervous
毎年台風が来ると緊張しますね
Because of landslides, right?
土砂崩れのせいですよね？
Every time an earthquake comes, we will be nervous
地震が来るたびに私たちは緊張します
don't know how much it will be
いくらになるか分かりません
Even recently, everyone is a little worried about the tsunami
最近でもみんな津波のことを少し心配しています
If you take the 46-year time scale of the entire earth
地球全体を46年という時間スケールで考えると
put it to the end of the day
一日の終わりに置いてください
This is what many people can see in books
これは多くの人が本で見ることができるものです
In this way to describe the history of our earth
私たちの地球の歴史をこのように説明してください
it has a total of 24 hours
合計24時間あります
In these 24 hours you
この 24 時間であなたは
Really, when we just said that bacteria capable of photosynthesis appeared
ほんとに、さっき光合成ができる細菌が現れたって言ったときに
It's almost morning
もうすぐ朝です
That is to say, after 9 o'clock
つまり9時過ぎ
Because it's 12 o'clock, so around 9 o'clock
12時だから9時くらいかな
it just appeared
それはちょうど現れた
before dawn
夜明け前に
what we can see
私たちが見ることができるもの
In fact, it's just the germ of life
実はそれは生命の芽生えに過ぎない
Sunshine bacteria only appear after dawn
太陽光バクテリアは夜明け後にのみ出現します
The emergence of blue-green algae has reached noon
アオコの発生が正午を迎えました
We just said that after the emergence of nucleated dimensional organisms
有核次元生物の出現後、と先ほど言いました。
Only then will there be real plants appearing behind
そうして初めて、本物の植物が背後に現れるでしょう
You see, the nucleated dimensional organisms are about a billion years old as we just said
ほら、先ほど言ったように、有核次元生物は約10億年前のものです
so it's already afternoon
だからもう午後だよ
then it was early
それなら早かった
I just said that there is an animal without vertebrae in Hanwuji
漢武寺には脊椎のない動物がいると言いました
In fact, it was almost 9:10 at night.
実際には夜の9時10分近くでした。
when plants appear
植物が現れるとき
It's actually been almost 11 years since now
実に11年ぶりになりますね
last less than an hour
1時間未満続く
Turret just showed up
タレットが現れたばかり
and then in the last three minutes
そして最後の3分で
not our kind
私たちの種類ではありません
If humans related to us appear
私たちと関係のある人間が現れたら
Just like Sun Wukong came out of "Huaguo Mountain"
孫悟空が「花果山」から出てきたように
Three minutes to make a fuss in the sky
空で大騒ぎする3分間
The earth is messed up
地球はめちゃくちゃだよ
So if you look at it over such a long time
それで、これを長い間見てみると、
If you take a look at this National Geographic magazine,
このナショナルジオグラフィック誌を見てみると、
Sharks may have lived on Earth for the last year
サメは昨年地球に住んでいた可能性がある
Is it right
そうですか
So how expensive is the long life
では、長寿命にはどれくらいの費用がかかるのか
I often say this to my wife
妻によくこう言います
Is it right
そうですか
Then nature has a very long time
それから自然には非常に長い時間があります
I think time is one of its deepest wisdoms
時間は最も奥深い知恵の一つだと思います
In other words, on Earth, if there is no time-tested
言い換えれば、地球上で、実績のあるものがなければ、
even if there is life to speak
たとえ話す人生があったとしても
It often skims like we say
よく言うように、それは簡単な流し読みであることがよくあります
Floating for admissions purposes
入場目的でフローティング
In fact, from the point of view of life
実は、人生という観点から見ると、
we can't say it doesn't make sense
意味がないとは言えません
But if it is better
しかし、それがより良い場合は、
It's like knowing, like a shooting star
知っているような、流れ星のような
Of course humans come into this world
もちろん人間はこの世に生まれてきます
You can see there is a long record
長い記録があることがわかります
If there are at least two species of hominids
少なくとも 2 種のヒト科動物が存在する場合
One is not the number of people but the number of ancient people, the other is the number of people
1つは人の数ではなく古代人の数、もう1つは人の数です
We will compare the number of people as a closer relationship with us
私たちとより近い関係として人数を比較します
In fact, about 5 million years from now to
実際、今から約500万年後、
7 million years is the latest data
700万年が最新のデータ
Maybe it will change, not necessarily
もしかしたら変わるかも知れませんが、必ずしもそうとは限りません
Is considered to be the first to break away from the black star
黒星から脱却するのは初めてとみられる
started to go in the direction of our humans
私たちの人間の方向に進み始めました
The earliest group, but it still belongs to ancient humans
最古のグループだが、依然として古代人類に属している
when the number of people
人の数のとき
The first type is probably Renren or Qiaoren
最初のタイプはおそらく Renren または Qiaoren です
There are two names to translate it
翻訳には2つの名前があります
Hablas is translated as a capable person by someone, and a clever person by someone else
ハブラスはある人には有能な人と訳され、別の人には賢い人と訳される
The reason is because they can make tools
理由は道具が作れるから
But from the perspective of the ancient Yuan
しかし、古代元の視点から見ると、
They already walk on two feet
彼らはすでに二本足で歩いています
It's just that their size, height, in all respects
ただ、彼らの大きさ、高さ、あらゆる点で
Looks like a chimpanzee
チンパンジーっぽい
But chimpanzees, beware
ただしチンパンジーは気をつけろ
It walks on four legs most of the time
ほとんどの場合は4本足で歩きます
It must have four legs when it runs
走るときは4本の足が必要です
Occasionally stand up like us
時には私たちのように立ち上がってください
So from this point of view
したがって、この観点からすると
In fact, from the earliest possible
実は、できるだけ早い時期から、
This place is almost 2 million years old
この場所は約200万年前のものです
Then into Africa's Homo erectus
そしてアフリカのホモ・エレクトスへ
Then to Homo erectus in Asia
そしてアジアのホモ・エレクトスへ
This place is almost 800,000 years old
この場所は約80万年前のものです
If we say that the 600,000 to 800,000 people in Beijing
北京の人口が60万人から80万人だとすると、
almost here
もうすぐここ
So the tree goes from like this
それで木はこうなります
You can watch our intelligence in this place
この場所で私たちのインテリジェンスをご覧いただけます
so this is like
これは次のようなものです
How do you say it's like a maze
迷路みたいってなんて言うの？
Go to this place and turn again
ここまで行ってまた曲がる
go here to be able to
ここに行くとできるようになります
I can't get over here
ここには行けない
In fact from this
実はこれから
To be able to transfer to our intelligence
私たちのインテリジェンスに転送できるようにするために
Our nearest neighbors are supposed to be the Leandertas.
私たちの最も近い隣人はレデルタス族であると考えられています。
A while ago in Indonesia found a
少し前にインドネシアで見つけました
They're about 20,000 away from our time
彼らは私たちの時代から約20,000離れています
20,000 years is very close
2万年はすぐそこまで来ている
But another one came out
でももう一つ出てきた
Most anthropologists currently believe that
現在、ほとんどの人類学者は次のように信じています。
Not from the same one
同じものからではありません
So it's from this one
それではこれからです
But this is still speculation
しかし、これはまだ推測です
We are not chief anthropologists
私たちは主任人類学者ではありません
but at least we know
しかし少なくとも私たちは知っています
in over a million years
100万年以上かけて
around 1.5 million years ago
約150万年前
Why do we call him material civilization
なぜ彼を物質文明と呼ぶのか
before dawn
夜明け前に
because of the time they were created
作成された時代のせいで
is very clear to see
とてもはっきりと見えます
with what we call the hands of others
私たちがいわゆる他人の手で
Traces of operation knocked out
操作の痕跡が消えた
Obviously a stone knife like this
明らかにこのような石のナイフ
It can already be used to cut tougher
より厳しい切断にもすでに使用できます
For example, thin skin presses and things like that
例えば、薄皮プレスとか。
So it's everyone or a coincidence
だからそれはみんなか偶然か
time from now
距離現在的時間
from about 1.5 million years ago
約150万年前から
over a period of more than two million years
200万年以上の期間にわたって
That
それか
It is very important, a kind of personnel that can be used by creatures like humans
とても大切な、人間という生き物が使える人材
We can also say tool
ツールとも言えます
The earliest we know we will use is the Beijinger
我々が北京人を起用することを最も早くから知っていたのは
Because there are many places in their holes that have been burned
穴の中は焼けているところが多いので
When we were studying in the early days, it was said that it was about 500,000 years away from now
私たちが初期に研究していたとき、それは約50万年前のことだと言いました
Judging from the current data, it must be at least 600,000 to 800,000 years old
現在のデータから判断すると、少なくとも60万年から80万年前のものと考えられます。
But when I was studying, many people thought
しかし、私が勉強していたとき、多くの人はこう考えていました。
Beijingers should be Chinese or Chinese
北京人は中国人か中国人であるべきだ
In particular, the two watersheds should not be the ancestors of the Huangke watershed.
特に、二つの流域は黄柯流域の祖先であってはなりません。
From the perspective of today's anthropologists, this should not be the case
今日の人類学者の観点からは、これは当てはまらない
The vast majority of anthropologists in our world today would believe that
今日の世界の人類学者の大多数は次のように信じているでしょう。
We flew from the east after several migrations
私たちは数回の移住を経て東からやって来ました
not from mainland China
中国本土出身ではない
fire is very important
火はとても大切です
Because if we use fire, it will probably make us cross the glacier.
火を使えば氷河を越えることになるだろうから。
Learn a little about the Ice Age
氷河期について少し学びましょう
so important to us
私たちにとってとても重要です
if you know the history
歴史を知っていれば
just know why a scientist
なぜ科学者なのかを知ってください
while looking at things
物を見ながら
Although we are concerned about our future
私たちは自分たちの将来に不安を感じながらも、
Sometimes very cautious and nervous
時々非常に慎重で神経質になる
But we won't be easily afraid
でも私たちは簡単には怖がらないよ
The longest glacier on earth
地球上で最も長い氷河
is in the alps
アルプスにあります
In fact, it's been a long time since what I just said
実は、今言ったことからかなり時間が経ちました
2.5 billion years 2.1 billion years
25億年 21億年
200 million years by 41 years
41年までに2億年
Evidence of glaciers everywhere
いたるところに氷河の痕跡
But within a million years
でも100万年以内に
at least 8 times
少なくとも8回
we watch the record
私たちは記録を見ます
This record in the last 1 million years
過去100万年間のこの記録
1 million years and 4 billion years
100万年と40億年
that time is very short
その時間はとても短いです
Now scientists only need to go to Greenland
科学者はグリーンランドに行くだけで済みます
or the North Pole
あるいは北極
find a way to put
置く方法を見つける
make a hole
打一個洞
beat into the ice
氷に打ち込む
Also because it has a welling hole layer
また湧出孔層があるため
The ice core can be beaten for several kilometers
氷床コアは数キロメートルにわたって破壊される可能性がある
The ice brought up can be analyzed for the
引き上げられた氷は、
dull atmosphere
鈍い雰囲気
you can know that time
あなたはその時間を知ることができます
Atmosphere Water Content Temperature 1 Million Years Ago
100万年前の大気 水分含有量 温度
All kinds of information can be obtained
あらゆる情報が得られる
So let's look at the above symbols to see
それでは、上の記号を見てみましょう
one two three four five six seven eight
一、二、三、四、五、六、七、八
it has eight stages written on it
8つの段階が書かれています
But I am a little curious why there are two
でも、なぜ2つあるのかちょっと気になります
Then why didn’t it write this? I don’t quite understand it.
ではなぜこれを書かなかったのかというと、よくわかりません。
But let's take a look at this picture
でも、この写真を見てみましょう
Here is the current average temperature
現在の平均気温はこちら
This is where there is more ice
ここは氷が多いところです
Here is a place with less ice
ここは氷が少ない場所です
So if you go this way, it means the ice age
つまり、この方向に進むと、それは氷河期を意味します
If you go this way, it means that the temperature is rising
この方向に行くと気温が上がるということです
So this place is closest to us in this ice and period
つまり、この場所はこの氷と時代において私たちに最も近い場所です
About 15,000 to 30,000 years
約15,000年から30,000年
still a long time, right?
まだ長いですよね？
Because 15,000 years seems very far away from us
15,000年はとても遠いように思えるから
But it is already the closest ice age to us
しかし、それはすでに私たちに最も近い氷河期です
The one farther away from us in a million years
100万年後、私たちからさらに遠く離れたところにあるもの
Like this seven million to here
このように700万がここまで
There should be an ice age of 7.5 million
750万人の氷河期が来るはずだ
Then around 600,000 years ago
それから約60万年前
So we just said the era of Beijingers
それで、私たちは北京人の時代について言いました。
such a big ice age
こんなに大きな氷河期
You see it's a million years old
100万年も経っているのがわかります
The record ice chess looks the coldest
記録的なアイスチェスは最も寒そうに見える
The stage where the temperature drops the most
最も気温が下がる段階
So if you don't know how to use fire like them
だから、もしあなたが彼らのように火の使い方を知らないなら
even with fire
火があっても
To survive such a long ice age
長い氷河期を生き抜くには
within 100,000 years
10万年以内に
You see, this period of time is 100,000 years
ほら、この期間は10万年です
Not 100,000 years, at least 50,000 years
10万年ではなく、少なくとも5万年はかかる
can you make it through
乗り越えることができますか
i think it's not that easy
そんなに簡単ではないと思う
Our most recent one lasted almost 15,000 years
私たちの最も新しいものはほぼ15,000年続いた
It's been a rare time
珍しい時代になりましたね
survive this period of time
この時期を生き抜く
The rest of the time you see on average every about 100,000 years
残りの時間は平均して約10万年ごとに見られます
Just a very big ice age
まさに大氷河期
So everyone's been talking
それでみんなが話し始めた
There are also people who are arguing
喧嘩してる人もいるよ
Maybe a new ice age is coming
もしかしたら新たな氷河期が来るかもしれない
But before the ice age came
でも氷河期が来る前に
We're Already Worrying About Our CO2
私たちはすでに CO2 について心配しています
will make us very short time
時間が非常に短くなります
The temperature drops further
さらに気温が下がります
If you go further down, you will break through
さらに下に行けば突き抜けます
The point where the temperature rises the most
一番温度が上がるポイント
So in this potential lens
したがって、この潜在的なレンズでは
is something we're very worried about is going to happen
私たちがこれから起こることを非常に心配していることです
But what does human beings have to do with this environment?
しかし、人間はこの環境とどのような関係があるのでしょうか?
pay attention
注意を払う
This is the brain of the black star
これが黒星の脳だ
Baby time and adult time
赤ちゃんの時間と大人の時間
When we don't look at Baby
ベイビーを見ないとき
look over here
ここを見てください
as an adult
大人として
The black star is about 390 cubic centimeters
黒い星の大きさは約390立方センチメートル
Then came the words of everyone
そして出てきたみんなの言葉は
Almost to close to 500 cm
500cm近くあります
cubic centimeter
立方センチメートル
we human beings are
私たち人間は
CC over 1300
CC1300以上
So big at least here
少なくともここではとても大きい
more than 4 times
4回以上
with this
これとともに
more than 3 times worse
3倍以上悪い
you will find
見つけるだろう
when this baby
この赤ちゃんがいつ
If it is compared to the pelvis of the parent star
親星の骨盤に例えると
very small
非常に少ない
So you probably rarely see
なので、あまり見かけないかもしれません
When the little black star was born
小さな黒い星が生まれたとき
is dystocia
難産です
Almost all natural births
ほぼすべての自然分娩
came out with one sound
一音で出てきた
But if people are going to be born now
でももし人がこれから生まれるとしたら
If he wants to come out directly
彼が直接出てきたければ
you will find the mother's pelvis
あなたは母親の骨盤を見つけるでしょう
The horizontal direction is wider
横方向が広い
The heavier direction is narrower
重い方向ほど狭い
If you're going to use directions like this
このような指示を使用する場合
If you squeeze it out like this
こうやって絞り出すと
very difficult
非常に難しい
So when a child is born
なので子供が生まれると
After the miserable
惨めな事の後に
Turn your head 90 degrees
頭を90度回転させてください
just came out
ちょうど出てきた
otherwise
さもないと
It is very easy to have dystocia
難産になりやすい
So chimpanzees to modern humans
つまりチンパンジーから現生人類まで
this brain
この脳
has changed a lot
非常に大きな変化がありました
This change doesn't look like it's going to do us any good
この変更は私たちにとって何の利益にもならないように見えます
because of dystocia
難産のため
so
それで
What is the human brain like?
人間の脳とはどのようなものなのでしょうか？
What effect did it have on us
それは私たちにどのような影響を与えましたか
take a look
見てください
we call hominid
私たちはヒト科動物と呼んでいます
Said that it's not that we only have human beings now
今は人間しかいないわけではないと言いました
but roughly very close
しかし、ほぼ非常に近い
Modern humans are within the genus Homo
現生人類はヒト属に属する
one of them is
そのうちの1人は
Let's see what characteristics he has
彼にはどんな特徴があるのか​​見てみましょう
Let's just skip the previous paragraph
前の段落は飛ばしましょう
He said that the size of old growth is necessary to grow
彼は、成長するには古い成長のサイズが必要であると言いました
Then our growth curve is weird
それなら私たちの成長曲線は奇妙です
where is the strangeness
どこがおかしいのか
the time our infancy comes out
私たちの幼児が生まれる時
Barely survived when born
生まれたときはかろうじて生き残った
If you take a scumbag out and leave it in the wild
クソ野郎を取り出して野に放っておいたら
it must not survive
それは生き残ってはいけません
Chimpanzees have a chance
チンパンジーにもチャンスはある
not ideal
理想的ではない
But when we look at Bambi's words
しかし、バンビの言葉を見ると、
It takes about 5 minutes after birth, and it can stand up after 10 minutes
生後5分程度で、10分ほどで立ち上がるようになります。
You can run with your mother
お母さんと一緒に走ってもいいよ
So the number of biological words
それで生き物の数は
Probably need the mother to take care of it when it is born
生まれたら母親が世話をする必要があるかもしれない
This is the characteristic of general martial arts
これが総合格闘技の特徴です
Then our childhood was very long
それから私たちの子供時代はとても長かったです
Usually 15 years or older to become an adult
通常15歳以上で成人となります
Because this time will be extended
今回は延長されるので
Our social structure has also changed
社会構造も変わりました
so all the numbers
それですべての数字が
usually a matriarchal society
通常は母系社会
or magnetic society
あるいは磁気社会
It is usually several magnetic entities
通常、それは複数の磁性体です
at the same time
同時
Take care of one or several babies
1人または数人の赤ちゃんの世話をする
For example, mother and mother's sister
たとえば、母親と母親の妹
and take care of her own daughter
そして自分の娘の世話をする
So we can imagine
それで私たちは想像することができます
Why our current monogamy
なぜ現在の一夫一婦制なのか
then not
それならそうではない
If you are monogamous and have to take care of children
一夫一婦制で子供の世話をしなければならない場合
especially took care of two three four
特に2、3、4を大事にしました
even if one
たとえ1つでも
if in taiwan
台湾なら
It's just that there are many parents helping
手伝ってくれる保護者がたくさんいるだけです
otherwise why say
そうでなければなぜ言うのか
It's really hard when you have to take care of children.
子供の世話をしなければならない時は本当に大変です。
You can see this social structure
この社会構造がわかります
It is indeed an opportunity for women to take care of children
女性にとっては子育てをするチャンスです
still more
より一層
That's because our tool increases meat wetness enhancement
それは、私たちのツールが肉の湿り気を強化するためです
So the body can become healthier
そうすれば身体はより健康になれます
Then we will have more adaptable athletic ability
そうすれば、より適応力のある運動能力が得られます
I think this ability
この能力だと思います
Especially in modern times it is called extreme sports, right?
特に現代ではエクストリームスポーツと呼ばれていますよね。
after being invented
発明されてから
It's really hot
本当に暑いです
human beings rely on the brain
人間は脳に依存している
Our athleticism is super
私たちの運動能力はスーパーです
making tools this is of course
道具を作るのはもちろんですが
our most special
私たちの最も特別な
in all tools
すべてのツールで
Lens language and text should be the most special
レンズの言語とテキストは最も特別なものである必要があります
I had a chat with Li Yuanshi during the meal just now
先ほど食事中に李源石さんと話をしました
Language is what we are born with
言語は私たちが生まれながらに持っているものです
Words were indeed invented by man
言葉は確かに人間によって発明された
same as science
科学と同じ
something invented by everyone
みんなで発明したもの
Usually it is not easy to learn
通常、学ぶのは簡単ではありません
so kids
だから子供たち
Especially we can't write Chinese characters well
特に漢字はうまく書けません
Often used to be beaten
よく殴られることがあった
This hope that this teacher and the little
この先生と小さな子どもたちが
Parents, don't often beat children's palms
親は子供の手のひらを頻繁に叩かないでください
It should not be so easy for every child to learn to write
すべての子供にとって、書くことを学ぶのはそれほど簡単ではないはずです
Humans actually have a very important stage
人間には実はとても重要な段階がある
It is an agricultural industry developed in collective life
集団生活の中で発展してきた農業です
I'll talk to you a little more later
後ほどもう少しお話します
but one important thing
でも一つ重要なこと
How we are different from other creatures
私たちは他の生き物とどう違うのか
is apart from the human power that we have inherited
私たちに受け継がれてきた人間の力とは別に
do we have a different part
違う部分があるの？
the way we live
私たちの生き方
traits that instill our existence
私たちの存在に影響を与える特徴
different from other creatures
他の生き物とは違う
That's how our culture actually affects us
それが私たちの文化が実際に私たちに与える影響です
Many places may be beyond our nature
多くの場所は私たちの自然を超えているかもしれません
biological nature
生物本性
we have just mentioned
先ほども述べました
If it is 15,000 to 30,000 years
15,000年から30,000年だと
It is human beings who have truly set foot on the
本当にその地に足を踏み入れたのは人類である
the stage of evolution
進化の段階
why do we say that
なぜそれを言うのか
because during this time
この間だから
Neanderthals disappeared from this earth
ネアンデルタール人は地球上から消えた
About 30,000 years from now
今から約3万年後
near
近く
They entered the ice age with us
彼らは私たちと一緒に氷河期に入った
But there is no way out
しかし、出口はありません
Humans in 15,000 years
15,000年後の人類
after the weather softens
天気が柔らかくなってから
Finally out of the ice age
ついに氷河期から脱却
After this turn around, it will be incredible
振り向いたらすごいことになるよ
Let's take a look at the extent of the impact of this ice age
この氷河期の影響がどの程度のものかを見てみましょう
The 18 means 18,000 years
18は18,000年を意味します
That is, when the Ice Age has not fully receded
つまり、氷河期が完全に後退していないとき
You look at all of Canada and the Great Lakes
カナダ全土と五大湖を見渡せます
and the north of the United States
そしてアメリカ北部
This white area is full of ice lakes
この白いエリアは氷の湖でいっぱいです
all covered
すべてカバーされています
so in
それで
The closest Ice Age to us
私たちに最も近い氷河期
Between Mainland China and Taiwan
中国と台湾の間
There is even a phenomenon of connection
繋がる現象もある
this is understandable
これは理解できます
then say
それから言う
this
これ
It's not just snowing, it's
ただ雪が降っているだけではなく、
Base ice is already in mainland China
吉氷はすでに中国本土にある
Accumulated to South China
中国南部に蓄積
base ice phenomenon
ベースアイス現象
It's not absolutely impossible
絶対に不可能というわけではない
in fact
実際には
snow in the south
南の雪
base ice maybe
ベースアイスかも
There is no way the base is so thick
ベースがこんなに厚いわけがない
but you can watch
でも見ることはできます
Canada
カナダ
almost covered in ice
ほぼ氷に覆われている
If we look at the nearest 8000 years from now
今から最も近い8000年後を見てみると
it's already hiding
それはすでに隠れています
I went to such a place
こんなところに行ってきました
of course
もちろん
now everyone is saying
今みんなが言ってる
This block of ice in the Arctic
北極にあるこの氷の塊
are under reduced
削減されています
you just know
あなたはただ知っています
why do you think
どうして...と思うのですか
very nervous
非常に神経質
good
良い
pass
合格
After the Bianhe period, you see, this is 13,000 years
扁河時代の後は、13,000年です。
the reality of human development
人間開発の現実
Already there are very inverse and surprising tools
すでに非常に逆で驚くべきツールがあります
like this is an ancient needle
これは古い針のようです
A needle made from a bone, you can see the meticulousness of its workmanship
骨から作った針、丁寧な仕事がわかる
On the surface, this piece seems to be the same as the period when the coincidence just made it
表面的には、この作品は偶然が重なってできた時代と同じように見える
Stone knives are a little bit similar
石ナイフも少し似ています
Actually, I'm sorry, it's still not the same
実はごめんなさい、まだ変わってないんです
Look at this piece, this is 4500 years
この作品を見てください、これは 4500 年です
In 4500, a machine appeared in Dakengkeng, Taiwan
4500年、台湾の大坑坑に機械が出現
That's where Basian is now
それがベイシアンの今いる場所です
I'm sorry, it should be the place of Badi
ごめんなさい、そこはバディの場所のはずです
Already some people's machines have appeared
すでに何人かのマシンが登場しています
A piece of news I heard recently is
最近聞いたニュースの一つは、
Matsu finds a bone that may be 7,000 years old
マツ、7000年前のものと思われる骨を発見
that was a little earlier
それは少し前のことでした
You know that we already have colleagues and people in Asia
ご存知のように、私たちにはすでにアジアに同僚や人々がいます
In Mexican words, in 4500 years
メキシコの言葉で言えば、4500年後
You see this building is very beautifully done
この建物はとても美しくできているのがわかります
The grinding case of his bones and stones
彼の骨と石を粉砕したケース
In fact, the 90s have already begun to move towards a new era
実は90年代はすでに新たな時代に向けて動き始めている
So let's look ahead a little bit
それでは少し先を見てみましょう
How did our people move forward?
私たちの人々はどのように前進したのでしょうか?
Here I tell you a story
ここで私はあなたに物語を話します
We've reached the point where we're near the end
終わりに近いところまで来ました
I tell you a story
お話をします
In fact the story was National Geographic
実際、この話はナショナルジオグラフィックでした
I found it from an article in 2002
2002年の記事から見つけました
what he calls a lost civilization
彼が失われた文明と呼ぶもの
But where did it disappear?
しかし、それはどこに消えたのでしょうか？
green sahara hard to imagine
緑のサハラは想像しにくい
Why does the Sahara Desert use green to describe him?
なぜサハラ砂漠では彼を表すのに緑が使われるのでしょうか?
The whole story happened in 2000
全ての話は2000年に起こった
At that time there was an archaeologist in Chicago
当時シカゴに考古学者がいました
His name is Sireno
彼の名前はシレーノです
this person is famous
この人は有名です
Because his discovery has been made into a movie
彼の発見は映画化されたので
There's at least one movie called "All the Evil"
「オール・ザ・イーヴル」という映画が少なくとも1本あります
Has anyone watched this movie
誰かこの映画を見ましたか
"The Evil Fish Thief"
「邪悪な魚泥棒」
10 times the movie of "Bad Fish" now
「Bad Fish」の映画が10倍になりました
So about the size of a dinosaur
つまり恐竜くらいの大きさ
It was very surprising to find the crocodile in the salad
サラダにワニが入っていたのにはとても驚きました
There is also a species of grass dragon found in Nileir
ナイルアには草竜の一種もいます
This is what he found
これが彼が見つけたものです
He just happens to be familiar with that area.
彼はたまたまその地域に精通しているだけです。
That's the Tarzan we'll mention later
それが後述するターザンです
The Desert We Call Tethered
私たちが繋がれた砂漠と呼ぶもの
The story actually goes like this
実際の話はこんな感じです
when they had an archaeological
彼らが考古学調査を行ったとき
Desert stability 120 degrees
砂漠の安定性 120 度
Fahrenheit of course
もちろん華氏
That's forty degrees now
今は40度です
it's amazing temperature
すごい気温ですね
They missed the exam for half a month
彼らは試験を半月欠席した
found nothing
何も見つかりませんでした
Also encountered bandits in Africa
アフリカでも山賊に遭遇
At that time some of them got separated
その時、何人かは別れてしまった
there is a photographer
写真家がいます
His name is Headware
彼の名前はヘッドウェアです
He found some kind-hearted human bones on a sand dune
彼は砂丘で心優しい人骨を見つけた
Now the words of the Tarzan desert
今、ターザン砂漠の言葉
we call it a desert within a desert
私たちはそれを砂漠の中の砂漠と呼びます
that is to say
つまり
Almost the driest area
ほぼ最も乾燥した地域
what did headware say
ヘッドウェアは何と言ったか
He said it seemed like there was a gust of wind in the desert
彼は砂漠に突風が吹いているようだと言いました
brought us to that place
私たちをあの場所に連れて行ってくれた
let's rest in that place
あの場所で休みましょう
But immediately on that side
でもすぐにあちら側で
He found something very unusual
彼はとても珍しいものを見つけた
In the tools he found the real thing, the building, the axe.
彼は道具の中に本物、建物、斧を見つけました。
Then the bone he found a lot of bone
それから彼は骨をたくさん見つけました
Including Lingyang's scenes of deer and aquatic animals
陵陽の鹿や水生動物のシーンを含む
Among them are crocodiles, hippos, turtles, and fish sticks.
その中にはワニ、カバ、カメ、魚の棒などが含まれます。
Why in the desert in such a dry desert
なぜこんな乾燥した砂漠に？
find something like this
このようなものを見つけてください
Includes bones and osteoids
骨と類骨が含まれます
sirino he is worthy of being an archaeologist
シリノ彼は考古学者にふさわしい
He is so fine that he is likely to stand in a place where he used to be
彼はとても元気なので、かつていた場所に立っているかもしれない
was once a plant
かつては植物だった
or at least the biological part
または少なくとも生物学的部分
in fact on the stony ground
実際、石だらけの地面の上で
You can still see that there are carvings out
まだ彫り物が残っているのがわかります
Carved out of this scene is the scene of a deer
この場面から彫られたのは鹿の場面です
So is there really a lot of creatures in that place?
では、その場所には本当にたくさんの生き物がいるのだろうか？
live in that place
その場所に住んでいます
Okay, let's talk about the Green Desert first.
さて、まずは緑の砂漠について話しましょう。
In fact, 70,000 years ago
実は7万年前
It's almost our kind of intelligence
それはほとんど私たちの種類の知性です
Start making one of the most important thousand joys on earth
地球上で最も重要な千の喜びの 1 つを作り始めましょう
When we talk about the process of flying from east to east or west to Qianxi
東から東へ、または西から銭渓へ飛ぶ過程について話すとき
At that time the salad desert was in fact
当時のサラダデザートは実は
its axis at that time
その時の軸は
70,000 years ago it was actually a desert
7万年前は実は砂漠だった
But 12,000 years ago
しかし1万2000年前
its axis actually wobbled a bit
その軸は実際には少しぐらつきました
In other words, after the Ice Age
つまり、氷河期が終わってから
12,000 years ago there was a swing
12,000年前にブランコがありました
The wind from Africa during that swing
そのスイング中にアフリカからの風
suddenly move north
突然北へ移動
That is, its rainfall suddenly shifts northward.
つまり、降雨量が突然北に移動します。
That is to say, many places in the whole area
つまり、エリア全体の多くの場所で
There is abundant rainfall
降水量が豊富です
What is the result of this abundant rainfall?
この豊富な雨の結果はどうなるのでしょうか？
You can watch these two pieces
この2作品を視聴できます
From this point of view
この観点から見ると
We usually like the light yellow area here
私たちは通常、側面の薄黄色の領域が好きです
the grassland we live in
私たちが住んでいる草原
this proportional angle
この比例角
If this place is green, like this dark green
ここが緑なら この深緑のように
is the rainforest
熱帯雨林です
Shallower, this place is said to be a grassland
もっと浅い、ここは草原だそうです
Now barely
今はかろうじて
This place is probably still grass
ここはまだ草だろう
This yellow place is all desert
この黄色い場所はすべて砂漠です
So we are talking about the area away from the green
つまりグリーンから離れたエリアについて話しているのです
It's this place called Gerborough
ここはガーボローと呼ばれる場所です
red dot this place
この場所の赤い点
totally yellow
完全に黄色
so currently it's desert
なので現在は砂漠です
70,000 years ago, it was also a desert
7万年前もここは砂漠だった
But twelve thousand years ago
しかし一万二千年前
became like this
このようになりました
that is its place
そこがその場所です
turned into a light green area
薄緑のエリアに変わりました
That is, a place with grassland
つまり草原のある場所
So in other words the Gerborough area
つまり、ガーボローエリア
In fact, there are green areas that are very dark green.
実際、非常に濃い緑色の緑の領域があります。
not only
だけでなく
In fact NASA even sent this space shuttle
実際、NASAはこのスペースシャトルも送った
Go to the photo taken above
上で撮影した写真に移動します
So the same is in the desert on the desert
同じことが砂漠の砂漠でも同じです
You can see the remains of the river beneath the ground
地下には川の跡が見えます
so there are very wide rivers
とても広い川があります
flow period
流過期間
you can see it along the top of the bed
ベッドの上に沿って見えます
In fact, some of the river dormitory
実際にはいくつかありますが、
How long ago did this happen
これはどれくらい前に起こりましたか
Back in the desert 3,500 years ago
3,500年前の砂漠へ
so we are now familiar
だから私たちは今ではおなじみです
The Chinese often say Shahai Shangtian, Shahai Shangtian
中国人はよくシャハイシャンティアン、シャハイシャンティアンと言います。
in fact the whole world
実際には全世界
There have been humans on the earth for 3500 years
人類は3500年前から地球上に存在しています
then he started drying again
それから彼は再び乾燥を始めました
so what's going on over there
そこで何が起こっているのか
Let's see in 2005
2005年を見てみよう
he went back to that place
彼はあの場所に戻っていきました
This time it's not just him
今度は彼だけではない
In fact another named Anna
実はアンナという名前のもう一人
go with him
彼と一緒に行きます
Anna is actually an anthropologist
アンナは実は人類学者です
when going with him
彼と一緒に行くとき
More human wills found
さらに多くの人間の意志が発見される
found two batches
2つのバッチが見つかりました
it's something special
それは特別なことです
These two chains
この2つのチェーン
one batch of time
一回分の時間
It should be about 4,000 to 6,000 years
4000年から6000年くらいかかるはず
Four thousand years to six thousand years from now
今から4千年から6千年後
They probably have mother races
彼らにはおそらく母なる種族がいるだろう
But another group earlier
しかし、その前に別のグループが
The time is about 8,000 to 10,000 years
その時間は8000年から1万年くらい
Ten thousand years is a very special number
一万年というのはとても特別な数字だ
their life is not oily wood
彼らの人生は油っぽい木ではない
they live by hunting
彼らは狩りをして生きています
So the way of life is very different
だから生き方も大きく違う
flyers
チラシ
That's why it's called the Tyranids
だからティラニッドと呼ばれる
Prayers
祈り
The two times are not the same
二つの時間は同じではない
where is the difference
違いはどこにありますか
If it is closer to the present
現代に近ければ
If the Tyranids come to see
ティラニッドが見に来たら
they are smaller
彼らはもっと小さいです
The front of the skull is higher
頭蓋骨の前部が高い
they can have some funeral things
彼らはいくつかの葬儀を行うことができます
like this is a volcanic stone
これは火山石のようです
And some crimes done with hippo bones
カバの骨を使った犯罪もある
At least they probably ran to
少なくとも彼らはおそらくそこに逃げた
volcanic fields hundreds of miles away
何百マイルも離れた火山地帯
pick up some jade
翡翠を拾う
but not sure
でもよくわからない
Or trade with others
または他の人と取引する
still picked it up
まだ拾った
not sure
わからない
but one thing is certain
でも一つだけ確かなことがある
their stone kisses
彼らの石のキス
There is already a phenomenon of penning sheep and cattle
すでに羊や牛を囲う現象が起きている
The other is the flyer
もう一つはチラシです
look at their tools
彼らのツールを見てください
yes can have
はい、持つことができます
With a hook, this hook is also very delicate, isn't it?
フックですが、このフックも非常に繊細ですよね。
I said its time is between 8,000 and 10,000
時間は8,000時から10,000時の間だと言いました
It's a lot to find and then you can look at its harpoon
見つけるべきものがたくさんあるので、その銛を見ることができます
It is also done quite delicately, using the current science
それは現在の科学を使用して非常に繊細に行われます
Especially if you look at it with chemical analysis, you can see
特に化学分析で見るとわかります。
Some of their living habits and diseases, for example, judging from their teeth
歯から判断するなど、生活習慣や病気の一部
They've started chewing some crude bone
彼らは粗末な骨を噛み始めた
Thick bone, not our current Pongalmi
太い骨、今のポンガルミではない
Obviously those sorghum or some thicker bones
明らかにモロコシかもっと太い骨です
If most of them are consecutive records, it is difficult to live beyond the age of 40
大半が継続記録だと40歳を超えて生きるのは難しい
From the franc implant of the tooth, a silk isotope can be found
歯のフランインプラントからはシルク同位体が検出される
That is, the same digit of the silk margin number, if we do dating analysis
つまり、年代測定をするとシルクマージン番号と同じ桁になります。
It can be known that they must drink fresh water
彼らは新鮮な水を飲まなければならないことが知られています
And fresh water must be available for father to drink
そして、父親が飲める新鮮な水が用意されていなければなりません
They don't have to travel very far to tell from their bones
骨から見分けるために遠くまで旅行する必要はない
You will find that anthropology uses many chemical analysis methods
人類学では多くの化学分析手法が使用されていることがわかります。
Bioanalysis can know all the situations of their lives
生体分析は彼らの生活のあらゆる状況を知ることができます
Judging from the bones of fish or shellfish they left behind
彼らが残した魚介類の骨から判断すると
They actually caught the Furnace Monster of the Nile
彼らは実際にナイル川の炉の怪物を捕まえた
I don't know what the furnace monster of the Nile didn't know
ナイル川の炉の怪物が何を知らなかったのか私には分かりません
You can only see it when you watch a movie in National Geographic magazine recently
最近はナショナルジオグラフィック誌の映画を見るときしか見られない
Some fish in the Nile are actually more than a few meters long
ナイル川の魚の中には体長が数メートルを超えるものもいます
very large fish belonging to the class of furnace fish
炉魚の綱に属する非常に大きな魚
Of course it also has other crocodiles and hippos
もちろん他のワニやカバもいます
These things all go together
これらはすべて一緒に起こります
I am a little bit moved by the fact that the Chinese say that a gentleman is in the end of the world, but he does not hide his name
中国人は「君子は世の終わりにいる」と言うが、彼はその名を隠さないことに少し感動した
But knowing the name sometimes doesn't help
しかし、名前を知っていても役に立たないこともあります
If you don't know the name, now dig out the bones
名前が分からないなら今すぐ骨を掘り出してから
After turning over the book, I can clearly see all the days I lived in the past
本をめくると、過去に生きた日々がはっきりとわかる
You can probably find out anything you've done.
おそらくあなたがやったことは何でもわかるでしょう。
In the end is a person living
結局人は生きているんだよ
Is it important for the survival of the group
それはグループの存続にとって重要ですか
Is the process important or the result important?
プロセスが重要ですか、それとも結果が重要ですか?
in front of nature
自然の前で
the ruthlessness of nature
自然の無慈悲さ
but we are also
しかし私たちもそうです
live by nature
自然とともに生きる
so I often feel
だから私はよく感じる
Life is often dependent on nature
人生は自然に依存していることが多い
provide opportunity
機会を提供する
But nature does not guarantee us
しかし、自然は私たちを保証しません
This sentence has been used by me often
この文は私がよく使っています
used in education
教育で使用される
I think the most important thing about education
教育で一番大事なことだと思う
It should be the principal of the school
学校の校長だったはずだ
Whether it is the director or the teacher
監督でも先生でも
should be available to those who study
勉強する人が利用できるようにする必要があります
Good environment
良い環境
For example, in college
たとえば、大学では
Principals should be responsible for creating an environment
校長は環境を整える責任がある
Let professors do research well
教授に研究をしっかりさせましょう
The professor should create a good
教授は良いものを作成する必要があります
laboratory environment or classroom environment
研究室環境または教室環境
Let students learn well
生徒たちによく学ばせる
So create the environment, create the opportunity
だから環境を作り、機会を作りましょう
but no guarantee
しかし保証はありません
Because no one after finishing college
大学を卒業しても誰もいないから
This life is a life
この人生は人生だ
it shouldn't be this kind of thing
こんなことであってはいけない
but take a look
でも見てください
Qi Feiren
チー・フェイレン
Why are you still staying in Gerbero in eight thousand years?
なぜ8000年後もゲルベロに留まるのか？
But there is no way when Gerbero lives for more than 4,000 years
でもゲルベロが4000年以上生きてるのにありえない
According to the logic, Gerbero District should have been around 3,500 years ago
理論によれば、ゲルベロ地区は約 3,500 年前に存在するはずです
It was turned into a desert area again
また砂漠地帯と化した
So what kind of environmental changes are they
では、どのような環境変化なのでしょうか
making them lose their ability to survive there
そこで生きていく能力を失わせる
this is a question worth asking
これは問う価値のある質問です
Some people say that self is also our modern self
自己は現代の自己でもあると言う人もいる
Bing and Zizi
ビングとジジ
But we're up to now and we're going to ask one thing
しかし、ここまでは終わったので、一つ聞いてみたいと思います
Why do people who come out of Bing and many
なぜ Bing や多くの人が
Everyone's fate is different
運命は人それぞれ違う
Some feet live longer and some feet live shorter
長生きする足もあれば短命な足もある
For example, this one is Australian
たとえば、これはオーストラリア人です
Australians now know
オーストラリア人はもう知っています
Before Europeans moved to Australia more than a hundred years ago
100年以上前にヨーロッパ人がオーストラリアに移住する前
They've been there for 40,000 years
彼らは4万年前からそこにいます
For 40,000 years, their lives have not changed much at all.
4万年の間、彼らの生活はまったく変わっていません。
Still a hunter's life a gatherer's life
依然として狩猟者の生活、採集者の生活
But more than a hundred years ago
でも百年以上前に
After the Europeans went in, they completely turned them over
ヨーロッパ人が入ってきた後、彼らは完全にひっくり返しました
We may ask why the social shadow of human beings
なぜ人間の社会的な影が存在するのか疑問に思うかもしれません。
It was Europeans who discovered America and Australia
アメリカとオーストラリアを発見したのはヨーロッパ人でした
Not Indians or Australians discovered Europe
ヨーロッパを発見したのはインド人やオーストラリア人ではない
I just mentioned the book by Jerr Diamond
先ほどジャー・ダイアモンドの本について触れました
He said how the fate of mankind actually happened
彼は人類の運命が実際にどのように起こったかを語った
This book is guns germs and steel
この本は銃の細菌と鉄です
Should be available now
今すぐ利用できるはずです
It's the textbook I use for my general studies
それは私が一般的な学習に使用する教科書です
he gave me good answers
彼は私に良い答えをくれた
A question I started asking around 40
40歳くらいから始めた質問
He gave me a lot of good inspiration in this book
彼はこの本で私にたくさんの良いインスピレーションを与えてくれました
So I also introduce to you
ということで、私も紹介させていただきました
We've just heard about the Inca Empire
インカ帝国について聞いたばかりです
Why are there so many glorious ancient civilization empires
なぜこれほど輝かしい古代文明の帝国が存在するのか
Can't live on in history
歴史の中で生き続けることはできない
Why the Civilizations of Western Europe Pray Big Today
西ヨーロッパの文明が今日大きく祈る理由
Why Western Europe invented science and technology
なぜ西ヨーロッパは科学技術を発明したのか
Is able to be chased by people all over the world
世界中の人から追われる可能性がある
See Jerr Diamond mentioned a story
ジャー・ダイアモンドがストーリーについて言及しているのをチェックしてください
This story doesn't really need him to tell us.
この話は彼に語ってもらう必要はありません。
Because if we just pay attention to the history of South America
なぜなら、南米の歴史にだけ注目してみると、
you can notice a story like this
このようなストーリーに気づくことができます
when the Incas were before the Europeans came in
ヨーロッパ人が入ってくる前のインカ人時代
It's actually really brilliant
実際本当に素晴らしいですよ
General Pizarro of Spain
スペインのピサロ将軍
In fact, when it came to the Inca Empire, it happened to be in
実際、インカ帝国に関して言えば、それはたまたま
columbus
コロンブス
Not long after discovering America
アメリカを発見してから間もなく
in the 16th century
16世紀に
when pizarro passed by
ピサロが通りかかったとき
On the plateau of Miru
ミルの高原で
Cajamarca was actually their Inca capital
カハマルカは実際には彼らのインカの首都でした
At that time the king was called Atahuapura
当時の王はアタワプラと呼ばれていました
his soldiers
彼の兵士たち
He has eighty thousand soldiers
彼には8万人の兵士がいる
He has no soldiers, he only has soldiers because
彼には兵士はいません、兵士だけがいるのです。
no horses in south america
南アメリカには馬がいない
only
それだけ
camel horses don't really have no horses as we see them now
私たちが今見ているように、ラクダの馬には実際には馬がいないわけではありません。
Pizarro only brought you can imagine
ピサロが持ってきたのは想像できるだけ
more than three hundred people
300人以上
Troops
軍
People of Wuhe
武河の人々
He splits
彼は別れる
62 cavalry plus 106 infantry
騎兵62名と歩兵106名
no expense one foot
不費一兵一足
Atahuapura
アタワプラ
then they
それから彼らは
After Zi De asked for about 60 cubic meters of gold
子徳が約60立方メートルの金を要求した後、
He still killed Atahuapra
彼はまだアタワプラを殺した
Europeans are brutal
ヨーロッパ人は残忍だよ
This war has become irresistible in the end
この戦争はついに抗えないものになった
The Inca Empire will never fight
インカ帝国は決して戦わない
So in this book
そこでこの本の中で
Jer Diamond mentioned why Europe is like this
ジャー・ダイアモンド氏はヨーロッパがなぜこのようであるかを語った
Defeat the Inca Empire
インカ帝国を倒す
the whole collapse
全体の崩壊
he mentioned something
彼は何かを言いました
Since the development of agriculture and wood industry in Mesopotamia in Europe,
ヨーロッパのメソポタミアでは農業や木材産業が発展して以来、
spread to continental Europe
ヨーロッパ大陸に広がる
allowed Europe to have an earlier time
ヨーロッパに早めの時間を与えることができた
have a larger population
人口が多い
Developed more effective imperial politics
より効果的な帝国政治を発展させた
And their cities are more complex
そして彼らの都市はより複雑です
Their function is in terms of the government system
彼らの役割は政府システムの観点からのものです
In terms of organizational structure
組織構造的には
can be seen from their cities
彼らの街からも見える
Like Rome, for example, you can see that
たとえばローマのように、次のことがわかります。
very systematic
非常に体系的な
Of course this caused their army to be professional
もちろん、これにより彼らの軍隊はプロフェッショナルになりました
technology needs professional
技術には専門家が必要です
Craftsmanship requires professionalism
職人技にはプロ意識が必要
All manufacture guns and swords
すべての銃と剣を製造
And there is the use of steel
そしてスチールが使用されている
So from these perspectives
したがって、これらの観点から
Europe has long been on the tools of civilization
ヨーロッパは長い間文明の道具を使ってきました
great strides
大きな一歩を踏み出しました
And the horse batch found in Central Asia
そして中央アジアで見つかった馬のバッチ
Make it more than just plowing the fields
単に畑を耕す以上のことをする
They are very effective in combat
彼らは戦闘において非常に効果的です
This is something that America doesn't have
これはアメリカにはないものです
America's empire is also divided
アメリカ帝国も分裂する
the most serious is
最も深刻なのは
Germs brought to America by Europeans
ヨーロッパ人によってアメリカに持ち込まれた細菌
Includes Smallpox and Metu
天然痘とメツを含む
make Europeans fully
完全にヨーロッパ人にする
making South Americans completely immune
南米人を完全に免疫にする
almost defeated
ほぼ負けた
All of a sudden it's just a disease
突然それはただの病気になる
thousands died
何千人も死んだ
There are a few other important things
他にも重要なことがいくつかあります
Including dissemination of text and information
テキストや情報の配布を含む
and social system
そして社会システム
manpower against different people
さまざまな人々に対する人材
and thinking habits are different
思考習慣も違うし
It shows that when two cultures meet
それは、2 つの文化が出会うとき、
Culture may not be good or bad
文化は良くも悪くもないかもしれない
But there are strengths and weaknesses
でも長所もあれば短所もある
this is reality
これは現実です
So there are two more important things
そこで、さらに重要なことが 2 つあります
one is text
1つはテキストです
We just said that the Inca didn't have a very effective script
インカにはあまり効果的な文字がなかったと先ほど言いました
They have language but no writing
彼らは言語を持っていますが、文字を持ちません
So actually their history has no foundation.
つまり、彼らの歴史には何の根拠もありません。
Not so in Europe
ヨーロッパではそうではない
texts and their dissemination of information
テキストとその情報の配布
In fact, they have long since made them socially
実際、彼らはずっと前から社会全体を作ってきました。
History, economy, and various systems are already very developed
歴史、経済、さまざまな制度がすでに発達している
So we said why didn't the Indians go to Europe
それで私たちは、なぜインディアンはヨーロッパに行かなかったのかと言いました
In fact, as Europe entered the Americas,
実際、ヨーロッパがアメリカ大陸に進出したとき、
They're past the time of the renaissance
彼らはルネッサンスの時代を過ぎた
all habits of thought
あらゆる思考習慣
We have entered the age of science
私たちは科学の時代に突入しました
ok let's see the best
よし、最高のものを見てみよう
The last few pictures are done, it's already 90 minutes
最後の数枚の写真が終わり、もう90分が経過しました
You'll find in plants and animals we say agriculture and wood
植物や動物の中で「農業」や「木材」と呼ばれていることがわかります。
When this wheat and rice was first made
この小麦と米が最初に作られたとき
Wheat was indeed in Mesopotamia 8,500 years ago
小麦は8,500年前にメソポタミアに確かに存在した
In Chinese words, rice is 7500 years old
中国語で言うと、お米は7500年前のものです
Then sheep and horses, horses were not domesticated until 3000 years ago in Central Asia
その後、羊と馬、馬は中央アジアで3000年前まで家畜化されませんでした。
So you'll find that not everywhere
どこにでもあるわけではないことがわかります
All have good food, all have good farming
全員が美味しい食べ物を持っており、全員が良い農業を営んでいる
There are good sheep herding environments everywhere, or there are flowing horses and sheep everywhere.
羊の飼育環境がどこにでもあり、馬や羊がどこにでも流れています。
Not so of course it can spread
もちろんそうではありませんが、広がる可能性があります
But the environment is not the same everywhere
しかし、環境はどこでも同じではありません
so what does it enlighten me about at the unit door
それで、ユニットのドアで私に何を教えてくれるのですか？
Malthus once said
マルサスはかつてこう言った
You actually when the population in your environment increases rapidly
実際、環境内の人口が急速に増加したとき、
food around you
あなたの周りの食べ物
food is about to decrease
食料が減りつつある
After the food is reduced
食事の量を減らしてから
The population may not be able to increase very quickly
人口はすぐには増えないかもしれない
So this is actually mutually restrictive
したがって、これは実際には相互制限です
But it may overlook one thing
しかし、一つ見落としがあるかもしれません
After the industrial revolution
産業革命後
Because mechanical force replaces human power, there is still force
機械の力が人力に取って代わられるため、依然として力は存在します。
so the personnel changed
それで人事が変わりました
In terms of people we have taken out from the natural world
自然界から取り出した人間に関しては
At that time began to be able to dig a lot of coal
石炭がたくさん掘れるようになった頃
generate steam and operate the machine
蒸気を発生させて機械を動かす
in this case
この場合
you will find one very important thing
あなたはとても重要なことを一つ見つけるでしょう
This may be my most critical header video of the day
これは今日の私の最も重要なヘッダービデオかもしれません
A noun called Karen Capacity
カレンキャパシティという名詞
What is Karen Capacity?
カレンの能力とは何ですか?
It's just how many people can an environment support?
問題は、環境が何人の人をサポートできるかということです。
There is no standard answer
標準的な答えはありません
We can ask the same question
私たちも同じ質問をすることができます
How many people can Taiwan's resources support?
台湾の資源で何人をサポートできるでしょうか？
Can support 23 million
2,300万をサポート可能
No problem at all
全く問題なし
Because we now have 23 million people living here
なぜなら、現在ここには2,300万人が住んでいるからです。
OK
OK
That can support 30 million
それは3000万をサポートできる
or 50 million
または5000万
If there are too few people
人数が少なすぎる場合
Do we have enough manpower?
人手は十分ですか？
so this is a very important concept
これは非常に重要な概念です
Malthus made a statement
マルサスが声明を発表
He said that if the population exceeds
人口がこれを超えると彼は言った
If this is the maximum population that can be maintained
これが維持できる最大の人口である場合
The changes that will occur to the environment
これから環境に起こる変化
The population will probably decrease
人口も減るだろうし
but he may not have noticed something
でも彼は何かに気づいていないかもしれない
The use of personnel will actually change the resource
人員を活用するとリソースが実際に変わります
we just mentioned
先ほど言いました
Interchange of personnel and materials
人的・物資の交流
Actually we are in this world
実は私たちはこの世界にいるのです
by what we just said
私たちが今言ったことによって
Materials produced by different personnel
さまざまな担当者が作成した資料
It's actually pretty amazing
実はかなりすごいんです
In fact, in the second century
実際、2世紀には
chemist proposes oil industry
化学者は石油産業を提案する
Like this, it's medium oil
こんな感じで中油です
This is probably Liuqing
これはおそらく柳清です
This should be the flower oil machine of the sea
これは海の花油製造機のはずだ
You can also see another one from the second century
2世紀の別のものも見ることができます
nuclear power of course
もちろん原子力も
This should also be our third nuclear plant
これも3番目の原子力発電所になるはずです
what does it bring
それは何をもたらしますか
Let's look at this population curve
この人口曲線を見てみましょう
the red one is
赤いのは
if your death rate is too high
死亡率が高すぎる場合
it can level off quickly
すぐに横ばいになる可能性がある
But if your mortality
しかし、もしあなたの死亡率が
not too high
高すぎない
if it maintains normal growth
正常な成長を維持していれば
rush up soon
すぐに駆けつける
So in terms of heavy axis
重軸に関して言えば
Here is almost what we see
ここに私たちが見ているものはほぼあります
this time in this place
今度はこの場所で
We are currently around 2010
現在は2010年頃です
almost here
もうすぐここ
so the place is about
それでその場所は約です
7 billion people
70億的人口
It should be 10 billion
100億あるはず
So 10 billion down
つまり100億ダウン
90 80 70
９０ ８０ ７０
around here
この辺です
So we're probably here
だから私たちはおそらくここにいる
So many people have been troubled for a while
ずっと悩んでる人が多すぎて
where are we going
私達はどこに行くの
probably current economists
おそらく現役の経済学者
and this human resource to the world
そしてこの人材を世界へ
more familiar
比較了解的
will tell us
私たちに教えてくれるでしょう
We'll probably go the purple route
おそらく紫の道を行くことになるでしょう
that is likely to go
それは行く可能性が高い
In this century, the population will exceed 10 billion
今世紀には人口が100億人を超える
In fact, based on our record
実際、私たちの記録によると、
look at this one
これを見てください
The current world population exceeded 700 million at the end of last year
現在の世界人口は昨年末に7億人を超えた
in the last century
前世紀に
In fact, just before the Second World War, it was just over 3 billion
実際、第二次世界大戦直前には30億ドル強でした。
So the doubling speed is very fast
倍速が非常に速いので、
The yellow one is to develop the country
黄色は国を発展させる
They were in fact during World War II
彼らは実際に第二次世界大戦中にいました
The population has started to decline
人口が減り始めた
When will the population of developing countries start to decline?
途上国の人口はいつ減少し始めるのでしょうか?
At least it will start slowly after 2000
少なくとも2000年以降は緩やかに始まるだろう
Only then will we start going down from this place
そうして初めて、私たちはこの場所から下り始めるのです
Therefore, the population of developed countries in the world
したがって、世界の先進国の人口は、
as a proportion of the population of developing countries
発展途上国の人口に占める割合として
In fact, the proportion of developing countries is still very high
実際、発展途上国の割合は依然として非常に高い
At least as far as the BRIC countries are concerned
少なくともBRICs諸国に関する限り、
BRIC means Brazil, Russia and India and China
BRICとはブラジル、ロシア、インド、中国を意味します
The population of these four countries
これら 4 か国の人口
should probably be
おそらくそうあるべきです
more than half of the world's population
世界人口の半分以上
because it was found that a large population
人口が多いことが判明したため、
he's gonna really start falling
彼は本当に落ち始めるだろう
in fact it will take a while
実際には少し時間がかかります
we said earlier
先ほども言いました
staff may not be adequate
人員が足りていない可能性がある
Based on our current population
現在の人口に基づく
human lifespan
人間の寿命
In fact, there are several curves here
実はここにはいくつかのカーブがあります
we can pay attention
私たちは注意を払うことができます
The most controllable is
最もコントロールしやすいのは、
use of personnel
人材の活用
If used in a valid situation
有効な状況で使用された場合
immediately have access to your technology
あなたのテクノロジーにすぐにアクセスできます
to control health problems
健康問題をコントロールするために
The most important hygiene should be drinking water
最も重要な衛生は飲料水であるべきです
If drinking water can be controlled
飲み水が管理できれば
your contagious disease
あなたの伝染病
if you get it under control
今すぐコントロールできれば
You'll see the death rate drop immediately
死亡率がすぐに下がるのがわかります
death rate drop
死亡率の低下
The birth rate also fell
出生率も下がった
In fact, after the death rate dropped
実際、死亡率が下がってからは
it's probably closer to ten percent of this place
おそらくこの場所の10パーセント近くです
nearest west
最も近い西
You can see it doing the second wave of descent
降下第二波が起こっているのがわかります
what is the disease it wants to control
コントロールしたい病気は何ですか
is a chronic disease
慢性疾患です
I have this disease too
私もこの病気です
reached a certain age
一定の年齢に達した
Probably neovascular disease and high blood pressure
おそらく血管新生疾患と高血圧
Three high questions
3 つの重要な質問
If chronic disease can be controlled
慢性疾患をコントロールできれば
The death rate can be lowered
死亡率は下げることができる
If you put developing and country
発展途上国と国を入れると
To make a comparison with developing countries
発展途上国と比較してみると
in terms of birth rate
出生率の観点から見ると
in terms of developing the country
国の発展という意味では
In fact, in the last century
実際、前世紀には
You will find that its death rate is already falling
死亡率はすでに低下していることがわかります
But if it is a developing country
でも発展途上国だったら
Its mortality rate is actually going to this century
その死亡率は実際には今世紀まで上昇する
just started falling from here
ここから落ち始めたばかりです
So to represent the population of the world
つまり、世界の人口を代表するには
Should be walking up for a while
しばらく歩いて登るはずだ
Probably can't escape until 101
たぶん101まで逃げられない
You will find different country desk
さまざまなカントリーデスクが見つかります
Survival and survival strategies are different
生存と生存戦略は違う
The last few three slides
最後の数 3 つのスライド
I will talk about this topic
このトピックについて話します
because i just said
私が今言ったばかりだから
Scientists actually look at things with a scope
科学者は実際にスコープを使って物事を観察します
That is to say, the target of your research
つまり、あなたの研究対象は、
In fact, there must be a specific goal
実際には、具体的な目標があるはずです
see things very precisely
物事を非常に正確に見る
But today we also found something
でも今日はまた何かを見つけました
Just use technology to see things
テクノロジーを使って物事を見るだけ
Sometimes it may not be enough
時には十分ではないかもしれません
Because what we live in this world is as a person
私たちがこの世に生きているのは人だから
If you look at things from a human point of view
人間の視点から物事を見てみると
may be different
違うかもしれない
Jerr Diamond he gave me the answer is also good
ジャー・ダイアモンドがくれた答えも良かった
problem is good
問題は良いです
that's it
それでおしまい
I list him one by one
私は彼を一人ずつリストします
Please take a look with me
ぜひ一緒に見てください
He said every civilization and every culture
彼は、あらゆる文明、あらゆる文化を言いました。
not necessarily immortal
不死ではないかもしれない
In fact, this is what we all want
実際、これは私たち全員が望んでいることです
Chinese culture is very difficult, especially hope
中国文化は非常に難しい、特に希望
Our children can obey the three rights
私たちの子供たちは 3 つの権利を守ることができます
Is it right
そうですか
Which of us doesn't wish for ourselves
私たちの中で自分自身を望まないのは誰ですか
As long as our children can obey the road and accept the three powers
私たちの子供たちが道を守り、三つの力を受け入れることができる限り
But he tells us that every civilization and every civilization
しかし彼は、あらゆる文明、あらゆる文明が、
Every culture may not be immortal
すべての文化は不滅ではないかもしれない
Not every civilization has been around for a long time
すべての文明が長い間存在してきたわけではありません
can be compared from a
から比較できます
on the face of it
表面的には
tools life aspects
道具の生活面
relatively backward
比較的後進的な
progress will develop
進歩は発展するだろう
This does not mean any discrimination
これは差別を意味するものではありません
For example, I just said Australia
たとえば、先ほどオーストラリアと言いましたが、
With no one competing with him in that place
あの場所では彼と競合する人は誰もいない
Isolated from this world for 40,000 years
4万年間この世から隔離されていた
After entering Europe, the whole turnaround
ヨーロッパに入ってから全体が好転
so not any civilization
だからどんな文明でもない
They must all go forward in a straight line or a curve.
それらはすべて直線または曲線で前進する必要があります。
not absolute
絶対的なものではない
Many tools, some difficult and some easy
多くのツール、難しいものもあれば簡単なものもある
It is more difficult as we just said
先ほども言ったように、それはさらに困難です
It was invented by humans themselves
それは人間によって発明されたものです
For example, it is difficult to say words
たとえば、言葉を発するのが難しい
science is hard
科学は難しい
These are not learned by everyone
これらは誰もが習得できるものではありません
So not everyone enters school
だから全員が学校に入学するわけではない
Both exams should have the same high marks
どちらの試験でも同じ高得点が得られるはずです
This is worth every Taiwan
これは台湾全体の価値がある
People who engage in education pay attention
教育に携わる人は注意してください
There are not many opportunities for real innovation in many things
多くのことにおいて真のイノベーションを起こす機会はそれほど多くない
many manufactured things
多くの工業製品
Many people learn from others
多くの人は他人から学びます
did not invent
発明しなかった
But there's nothing wrong with learning from others.
しかし、他人から学ぶことは悪いことではありません。
The development of much of our knowledge
私たちの知識の多くの発展
many ways of thinking
たくさんの考え方
i just said
私はちょうど言いました
Especially when it comes to things like words and science
特に言葉や科学などに関しては
Someone invented it first
誰かが最初に発明した
let's learn
学びましょう
well-educated and poorly-learned
高学歴と低学力
Depends on our talent and hard work
私たちの才能と努力次第
But he said something
でも彼は何か言いました
Whoever runs first is not necessarily the winner
先に走った人が必ずしも勝者とは限りません
Winning now may not always win
今勝っても必ず勝てるとは限らない
I often say this
私はよくこれを言います
is worth our vigilance
警戒する価値がある
Whoever runs first doesn't necessarily win.
先に走った人が必ずしも勝つとは限りません。
because if you look at
なぜなら、見てみると
The earliest places where agriculture developed
農業が最も早く発展した場所
Youwa language
養和留語
messed up now
現在一塌糊塗
If it weren't for the private oil produced elsewhere
他の場所で生産された民間石油がなかったら
Hold on to other places first
他地方先持上
The situation in the Middle East lives in many places
中東情勢は各地に広がっている
Of course he also has
もちろん彼も持っています
very rich people there
そこにはとても裕福な人たちがいる
then you go to africa
それからあなたはアフリカに行きます
Africa is not the best place to live
アフリカは住むのに最適な場所ではない
In fact, the most starved to death every day is also in Africa
実際、毎日最も多くの餓死者が出ているのもアフリカです
Those who win now may not always win
今勝っている人が常に勝てるとは限らない
Of course, the current winners may also become losers.
もちろん、現在の勝者が敗者になる可能性もあります。
But those who destroy their own resources are always the losers
しかし、自分自身の資源を破壊する者は常に敗者となる
Because civilizations that disappeared like this have already appeared on the earth several times
こうやって消えた文明はすでに何度か地球上に現れているから
That's what I just said maybe this paragraph
それが私が今言ったことです、おそらくこの段落
The most important sentence at the beginning of today's speech
今日のスピーチの冒頭の最も重要な一文
Once any kind of life is developed
あらゆる種類の生命が発達すると、
When breaking through the technical civilization of carrying capacity
収容力の技術文明を突破するとき
may have to accept the challenge of a personnel crisis
人事危機という課題を受け入れなければならないかもしれない
In other words, when we have developed such a sophisticated technology
つまり、これほど高度な技術が開発されたら、
we need enough people and supplies
十分な人材と物資が必要です
to support the increased population we need
私たちが必要とする人口増加をサポートするために
and the technologies we develop
そして私たちが開発するテクノロジー
it's necessary
それは必要です
But have we noticed what we consume
しかし、私たちは自分が何を消費しているか気づいていますか
there is no chance to fill
埋めるチャンスはない
Probably everyone in Taiwan should notice
おそらく台湾の皆さんは気づいているはずです
We have exhausted the resources of our descendants
私たちは子孫の資源を使い果たしました
An Evolutionary Perspective Head of Nature
進化の視点 自然の主
Humans are not the center of this natural world most of the time
ほとんどの場合、人間はこの自然界の中心ではありません
Will we be the center of the world in the future?
将来、私たちは世界の中心になるのでしょうか？
Not necessarily, right?
必ずしもそうとは限りませんよね？
The emergence of humans may be an accident of nature on earth
人間の出現は地球上の自然の偶然かもしれない
Evolution does not have a definite direction
進化には明確な方向性はない
Maybe we just took an opportunity
もしかしたら私たちはチャンスを掴んだだけなのかもしれない
If we look at our current human beings in this world
この世界の今の人類を見てみると
Its time is actually only tens of thousands of years
その時間は実際にはわずか数万年です
We have evidence to back our time up to only a few tens of thousands of years
私たちはわずか数万年までの時間を裏付ける証拠を持っています
There is a natural law, a biological context, and an environmental context
自然法則、生物学的背景、環境的背景があります。
it has a background
それには背景があります
brought us to where we are today
私たちを今日の場所に導いてくれました
can we think about it
それについて考えてみませんか
When biological evolution has no way to move forward effectively
生物学的進化を効果的に進める方法がないとき
Changes in our environment and changes in our culture
環境の変化と文化の変化
Is it when we live in this world
私たちがこの世界に生きているときですか？
special attention should be paid
特別な注意を払う必要があります
In other words how do we live
言い換えれば、私たちはどうやって生きていくのか
and how the people around us live
そして私たちの周りの人々がどのように生きているか
Should it become the focus of our thinking?
それが私たちの思考の焦点となるべきでしょうか？
Of course, this is what I often tell my students in class
もちろん、これは私が授業中に生徒たちによく言うことです
Now that we have stood on this stage of nature
この大自然の舞台に立った今
after thinking about it
それについて考えた後
And thinking about the manpower of tomorrow
そして明日の人材について考える
So should we be responsible for tomorrow?
では、私たちは明日に責任を持たなければならないのでしょうか？
Responsible for the environment and culture
環境と文化に責任を持つ
A lot of questions were when Jerr Diamond read that book
ジャー・ダイアモンドがあの本を読んだとき、多くの疑問が湧いた
I'm asking
私は尋ねている
How can life on earth last forever?
どうして地球上の生命は永遠に続くのでしょうか？
what kind of environment to live in
どのような環境で生活するか
What kind of environment do we live in?
私たちはどのような環境で生きているのでしょうか？
what are we
私たちは何ですか
what kind of creature is it
それはどんな生き物ですか
You will find that if other creatures
他の生き物ならわかるでしょう
For example, a goldfish that landed in the Pacific Ocean
たとえば、太平洋に落ちた金魚。
Did he know he was near an island
彼は自分が島の近くにいることを知っていましたか
or near the west coast of a Pacific Ocean
または太平洋の西海岸近く
probably not
おそらくそうではありません
But we are concerned about our environment
しかし、私たちは環境を心配しています
can be very clear
非常に明確にできる
we now know more and more
私たちは今、ますます多くのことを知っています
what kind of creatures are we
私たちはどんな生き物なのか
our surroundings
私たちの周囲
I know more and more where the same
同じ場所がどんどんわかってくる
Where is the difference
違いはどこにありますか
Our Taiwan can live such a good life
私たちの台湾はとても良い生活を送れます
what can we do
私たちは何ができる
Why can we communicate with many advanced countries
なぜ多くの先進国と通信できるのか
Enjoy the relative advantages and disadvantages of material life
物質的な生活の相対的な利点と欠点を楽しむ
What exactly is collective intelligence?
集合知とは一体何なのでしょうか？
can we see our future
私たちの未来は見えますか
When I was designing my own general education course
自分の一般教育コースを設計していたとき
In fact, many things about Taiwan
実は台湾についてはいろいろなことが
i don't have an answer
答えがありません
But I guess it's all of us
でもそれは私たち全員だと思う
Let's plan together how we will go in the future
今後どうなっていくのか一緒に計画しましょう
it may not have a certain right and wrong
特定の善悪があるわけではないかもしれない
But as long as we all agree
しかし、私たち全員が同意する限り、
What direction should we go
どの方向に進むべきか
For example, Taiwan has no personnel
例えば台湾には人材がいない
Then do we want to increase the price or not?
では、値上げするかどうか？
if no price increase
値上げがなければ
how do we use our people
人材をどのように活用するか
Then we don't lack water resources
そうすれば水資源には困らない
Most of the water on our mountains now
今、私たちの山のほとんどの水は
Once down, it will flow to Hainan.
下りると海南へ流れます。
How do we use our water resources
水資源をどのように利用するか
be used with caution
慎重に使用してください
i think these things
私はこれらのことを思います
It's not absolutely right or wrong
絶対的に正しいとか間違っているというわけではありません
But maybe we have to find it together
でも多分私たちは一緒にそれを見つけなければならない
way of living together
一緒に暮らす方法
ok thank you all
わかりました、皆さんありがとう
I see you need some water
水が必要なようですね
ok the rest of the time i think
わかりました、残りの時間は私が考えます
asked a lot of questions
たくさんの質問をしました
Some secretly suggested that I have no answer
私に答えはないのではないかと密かに示唆する人もいた
so do it again
だからもう一度やってください
Any questions or comments welcome
ご質問やコメントは大歓迎です
Thank you Professor Chen Zhuting for your speech
陳珠庭教授、ご講演ありがとうございました
I heard and learned a lot
たくさん聞いて勉強になりました
Just mentioned that there are 23 million people in Taiwan
先ほど台湾の人口は2,300万人と言いましたが、
We should have enough food now
もう十分な食べ物があるはずです
Because it can feed so many people
たくさんの人に食べさせられるから
If there are more in the future, it may not be enough.
将来的には、多すぎると足りなくなる可能性があります。
In fact, our food shortage in Taiwan is serious
実は台湾の食糧不足は深刻なのです
Because our autonomy is only 32%
私たちの自主性は 32% しかないからです
Most are imported
ほとんどが輸入品です
if not imported
輸入されていない場合
We can't actually live that many people
実際にはそんなに多くの人が住むことはできない
something went wrong
何か問題が発生しました
The energy part is
エネルギーの部分は、
I think we should really save
本当に節約すべきだと思う
what should be raised
何を上げるべきか
both but perhaps more importantly
両方ですが、おそらくもっと重要なこと
We should develop the energy of the future
私たちは未来のエネルギーを開発すべきです
R & D technology
研究開発技術
How about in the future there will be
将来的にはどうでしょうか
That is to say, there are technologies available to others
つまり、他人が利用できるテクノロジーがあるということです。
and then get energy harvested elsewhere
そして他の場所でエネルギーを収穫する
e.g. priesthood energy
例：神権のエネルギー
that may be my new technology
それは私の新しい技術かもしれません
technology is then transferred to other countries
そして技術は他の国に移転される
What about getting the first prize in our economy?
私たちの経済でトップの座を獲得してはどうでしょうか？
similar to this one
これに似たもの
that now
那現在
More influential when dealing together
一緒に取引するとより大きな影響力が得られる
we are now that
私たちは今それです
Research and development related to energy in Taiwan
台湾におけるエネルギー関連の研究開発
The money spent is really
使ったお金は本当に
really too little too little
本当に少なすぎる
So this is a bad phenomenon
つまりこれは悪い現象です
Then we didn't have oil
そのときは石油がなかった
That's not much coal
石炭はそれほど多くない
Other energy natural gas liquids are rare
他のエネルギーの天然ガス液体はまれです
that is no way
それはありえない
because we don't have that many resources
私たちにはそれほど多くのリソースがないので
But our brain power should be able to blossom
でも、私たちの脳の力は開花できるはずです
new technologies can be developed
新しい技術が開発できる
This is our hope for the future
これが私たちの未来への希望です
But this aspect is obviously less thoughtful.
しかし、この側面は明らかにあまり考慮されていません。
probably should have said
おそらく言うべきだった
We are now 2300
今は2300です
Three million people live as if we have enough resources
300万人が十分な資源があるかのように暮らしている
I don't look too worried
あまり心配していないように見える
Although most people talked about what fuel and electricity will increase
ほとんどの人は燃料と電力が増加することについて話していましたが、
everyone get nervous
みんな緊張する
But in the way of life, it seems that there is no shortage of resources
しかし、生活の面では、リソースが不足しているようには見えません
This is actually
これは実際には
No, Taiwan is really
いや、台湾は本当に
Often when an idea comes up
アイデアが浮かんだときによくあるのは、
There are actually many different voices, right?
実際にはいろんな声がありますよね？
we all know a lot
私たちはみんなたくさんのことを知っています
So in terms of social decision-making
つまり、社会的意思決定という観点から見ると、
There are many places where there are actually bottlenecks
実はボトルネックになっているところがたくさんある
In terms of planning
企画面では
I often say three words
私はよく三言言います
Also for the board of education
教育委員会にも
I said there are a lot of talents in Taiwan
台湾には才能のある人がたくさんいると言いました
few teams
少数のチーム
Then there are a lot of jobs in Taiwan
台湾には仕事がたくさんある
but few ideas
しかしアイデアは少ない
Taiwan has many plans
台湾にはたくさんの計画があります
This is for us probably
これはおそらく私たちのためのものです
This research unit
この研究ユニットは
But the cumulative effect is little
でも累積効果は少ない
So it seems that nothing has changed and accumulated like this
だから何も変わらずにこのまま積み重なっていったような気がする
a more collective common wisdom
より集合的な共通認識
Might be when I'm thinking about this aspect of the speech
スピーチのこの側面について考えているときかもしれません
An idea that is always in my heart
いつも心の中にある想い
no absolute answer
絶対的な答えはない
But we are in a relatively negative cycle
しかし、私たちは比較的負のサイクルの中にいます
when jumping out of the vortex
渦から飛び出すとき
Sometimes I feel a little weak
時々少し弱さを感じることがある
But it seems that we really want to be together
でも、本当は一緒にいたいみたいです
especially us
特に私たち
I think our academia may
私たちの学術界はそうかもしれないと思います
should do something more
もっと何かをすべきだ
too broad
広すぎます
However, the average human being is also very flexible.
しかし、平均的な人間は非常に柔軟でもあります。
So can withstand pressure
だからプレッシャーにも耐えられる
Can't beat the whole civilization
文明全体には勝てない
just like loss
まるで喪失のように
But actually another thing
しかし、実際には別のこと
It's you, the whole world is 7 billion
たとえ全世界が70億人だとしても、それはあなたです
But only about 1% of people
でも、ほんの1%くらいの人だけ
may want to use or his resources
彼のリソースを使いたいかもしれない
maybe more than 90%
おそらく90％以上
It's a very balanced
とてもバランスが取れています
so you say carrying capacity
だから収容力って言うのね
what is this place called
ここは何と呼ばれる場所ですか
weight ratio
重量比
an african man
アフリカ人男性
resources consumed by him
他的所消耗的資源
resources consumed by a civilized nation
文明国が消費する資源
It's very different
それはとても違います
Saved people after a long time
久しぶりに人を救った
What percentage of the world's talent is the United States
世界の人材の何パーセントが米国であるか
But the energy he consumes may be 670 percent
しかし、彼が消費するエネルギーは 670% である可能性があります。
seems to be usually capable
普通に有能なようだ
I feel free to take other people's things first and use them.
他の人の物を遠慮なく最初に受け取り、使用します。
this may change
これは変わるかもしれない
hello mr chen
こんにちは、チェンさん
so i want to ask
それで聞きたいです
Because this topic is about sustainable civilization
このテーマは持続可能な文明に関するものであるため、
sustainable civilization
持続可能な文明
Then I want to ask
それから聞きたいのですが
As for Mr. Chen's vision for both energy and human beings
チェン氏のエネルギーと人類に対するビジョンについて
maybe not to the whole world
もしかしたら全世界に向けてではないかもしれない
At least in Taiwan about energy
少なくとも台湾ではエネルギーに関しては
or about our entire vision of using energy or matter
またはエネルギーや物質の使用に関する私たちのビジョン全体について
Then I would like to ask Professor Chen
それでは陳教授にお聞きしたいと思います。
Thanks
ありがとう
with just
ただで
the same as the one mentioned
言及されたものと同じです
In fact, some things have no definite answer
実際、明確な答えがないものもあります
but in the race
しかしレースでは
For example, new personnel and new materials
例えば、新しい人材や新しい資材など
currently running
現在実行中
Is that the person in the immediate situation
それが当面の状況にある人ですか
find the answer
答えを見つける
Then solve it more effectively
そうすれば、より効果的に解決できます
For example, how much
たとえば、いくら
How many problems are solved
どれくらいの問題が解決されましたか
This is actually in a situation where there is no standard answer
実はこれ、標準的な答えがない状況なんです
side by side
並んで
For example, in terms of banning people in Taiwan,
たとえば、台湾での入国禁止に関しては、
Most experts don't think that's an effective solution to the problem
ほとんどの専門家は、それが問題の効果的な解決策であるとは考えていません
How many percent can the Sun people solve?
太陽の民は何パーセント解けるでしょうか？
seems to have an estimate
見積もりがあるようです
But after we made the Taiwan Sunman version,
でも、台湾サンマンバージョンを作ってから、
Most of them are exported
そのほとんどが輸出されている
I'm useless
私は役に立たない
The reason is to cooperate
理由は協力するため
Technology didn't play well together
テクノロジーがうまく連携できなかった
Then under the condition of relatively high price
それから比較的高い価格の条件で
At least not currently
少なくとも現時点ではそうではない
Taiwan does not use much solar energy
台湾は太陽エネルギーをあまり使用しない
Most of them are exported to other places
それらのほとんどは他の場所に輸出されています
Especially in Europe, we export a lot
特にヨーロッパに多く輸出しています
Like this thing actually it
このことのように、実際にはそれ
Of course there are possible solutions
もちろん可能な解決策はあります
The most direct one is
最も直接的なのは、
Should Taiwan Confront Nuclear Energy?
台湾は原子力エネルギーに立ち向かうべきか?
Then this one takes the lead in our entire social hierarchy
そして、この人が私たちの社会階層全体で主導権を握ります
is a knotted problem
複雑な問題です
There is currently no good solution
現時点では良い解決策はありません
so i say something like this
だから私はこのようなことを言います
It's a lot like our own life sometimes
それは時々私たち自身の人生によく似ています
You sometimes have to face making a decision
時には決断を迫られることもある
then it may be a painful decision
そうなると、それは苦渋の決断になるかもしれない
may be take it or leave it
受け取るか放置するか
can be a decision
決断できる
But it's at least a decision
でも少なくともそれは決断だ
Then we sometimes make this kind of decision in life.
そして、私たちは人生において時々このような決断を下します。
After doing it, I will continue to move forward
やり遂げた後は、さらに前進していきます
Instead of just stopping at one location
一つの場所に止まるのではなく、
Then everyone seems to be arguing
そしたらみんな喧嘩してるみたいだ
That's the material
それが材料です
I think from the perspective of my chemistry
私の化学の観点から考えます
We have a lot of resources that can be used for new creations
新しい創作に使用できるリソースがたくさんあります
I think it's cute
かわいいと思います
People are more critical in terms of technology
人々はテクノロジーに関してより批判的になっています
I dare not speak directly
直接話す勇気はない
For example, let’s talk about a few more likely to be compatible with our hopes.
たとえば、私たちの希望と一致する可能性が高いものについていくつかお話しましょう。
Is it right?
そうですか？
Available before 2050
2050 年より前に利用可能
Seems like a big question mark so far
これまでのところ大きな疑問符のように思えます
If it cannot be developed effectively before 2050
2050年までに効果的に開発できない場合
Opportunity to express
表現する機会
the one that cost a lot of money
たくさんお金がかかったもの
And not all countries can't use it
すべての国が使用できないわけではありません
Is it forcing some countries to engage in nuclear fission?
それは一部の国に核分裂を強制しているのでしょうか？
Taiwan must at least import oil
台湾は少なくとも石油を輸入しなければならない
So this probably won't work
だからこれはおそらくうまくいかないでしょう
We don't have such personnel here
ここにはそのような人材はいません
So maybe you need to think about it this way
なので、こういう風に考えてみるといいかもしれませんね
The other BIOMASS now
もう一つのバイオマスは今
It also involves arguing about whether food should be used in this way
また、食品をこのように使用すべきかどうかについての議論も含まれます。
So I think this kind of thing needs to be done to make a clarification.
したがって、このようなことを明確にする必要があると思います。
Why did I emphasize on seeing things from the perspective of science majors?
なぜ私は理系の視点から物事を見ることを重視したのでしょうか？
Seeing things differently from a non-scientific perspective
非科学的な観点から物事を違った視点で見る
But it's not the same. If you use the opposite
しかし、それは同じではありません。逆に使用すると、
a lot of trouble
たくさんのトラブル
But if it is used to talk about it
でもそれについて話すのに使われるなら
I think maybe we can find some ways to improve
もしかしたら改善する方法が見つかるかもしれないと思う
I'm a little bit more optimistic about resources than people
私は人よりも資源について少し楽観的です
Because the resource actually should be full on Earth in some way
なぜなら、資源は実際には何らかの形で地球上に満ちているはずだからです。
You can use time in exchange for conditioning
コンディショニングと引き換えに時間を使うことができる
The words of the staff are not enough
スタッフの言葉だけでは足りない
Immediately the industry is like Taiwan's industry, it should be affected immediately
この業界は台湾の業界と同じようになり、すぐに影響を受けるはずです
I believe that economy will be affected immediately
すぐに経済に影響が出ると思います
Of course, there is a problem involved here, that is,
もちろん、ここには問題が含まれています。
What kind of economic indicators should Taiwan use?
台湾はどのような経済指標を使用すべきでしょうか?
to plan for growth
成長を計画する
So what is the problem
それで何が問題なのか
should or should not
すべきかすべきではないか
It also apparently has a different answer
それも明らかに違う答えがある
some people think that means
それが意味すると考える人もいます
If there is no economic growth
経済成長がなければ
How can we live a better life
どうすればより良い生活を送ることができるでしょうか
But the economy is doing better
しかし経済は良くなっている
Is everyone sure
みんな本当ですか？
an ideal society
理想的な社会
I'm not sure either
私もよくわかりません
So questions like this are usually on the table in Taiwan
したがって、このような質問は台湾では通常のテーブルにあります
less people talk about it
それについて話す人が減った
Your question may not be able to be provided by me alone
あなたの質問は私だけでは答えられないかもしれません
I can tell you simply
シンプルに言えるのは
From the perspective of certain money-paying technologies of science
お金を支払う特定の科学技術の観点から
We need to be on certain material resources
特定の物質的資源を利用する必要がある
to move forward
前進する
Advanced technology takes a few more steps
高度なテクノロジーにはさらにいくつかのステップが必要です
still have a chance
まだチャンスはある
this is no problem
これは問題ありません
I dare not speak
スタッフ あえて話さない
I don't know if Teacher Wang treats the personnel right?
王先生が人事を正しく扱っているかどうかはわかりませんが？
is there any way
何か方法はありますか
There may be some more here
ここには他にもあるかもしれません
This expert may have a better answer than me
この専門家は私よりも良い答えを持っているかもしれません
I will compare
比較してみます
I think it's almost time
そろそろ時間だと思う
we are very happy today
私たちは今日とても幸せです
Professor Chen gave us a very
チェン教授は私たちにとても貴重なご意見をくれました。
widely
広く
Then it also caused everyone to go back and think about it.
そして、それはまた、誰もが振り返って考えるきっかけにもなりました。
some problems
いくつかの問題
ok thank you very much
はい、ありがとうございます
Thank you Professor Chen
陳先生、ありがとうございました
thank you all
皆さん、ありがとうございました
thank you very much
どうもありがとうございます